<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble motion vvith submission vnto the right Honorable LL. of Hir Maiesties Priuie Counsell VVherein is laid open to be considered, how necessarie it were for the good of this lande, and the Queenes Majesties safety, that ecclesiasticall discipline were reformed after the worde of God: and how easily there might be provision for a learned ministery.</title>
            <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7754</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100621</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836453</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836453</idno>
            <idno type="VID">728</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21448)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 728)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 220:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble motion vvith submission vnto the right Honorable LL. of Hir Maiesties Priuie Counsell VVherein is laid open to be considered, how necessarie it were for the good of this lande, and the Queenes Majesties safety, that ecclesiasticall discipline were reformed after the worde of God: and how easily there might be provision for a learned ministery.</title>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>111, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Waldegrave],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Penry.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and publication place from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An humble motion to the LL. of the Counsell.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Training of --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church discipline --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:728:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:728:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN HVMBLE MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION VVITH SVB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISSION VNTO THE RIGHT HONORABLE LL. OF HIR MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIES PRIVIE COVNSELL.</p>
            <p>VVHEREIN IS LAID OPEN TO be conſidered, how neceſſarie it were for the good of this Lande, and the Queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſafety, that Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline were reformed after the worde of God: And how eaſily there might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for a learned Miniſtery.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>REVEL. 3.20.</bibl>
               <p>Behold I ſtand at the dore and knock: if any man heare my voice and open the dore, I will come in vnto him, and will ſuppe with him, and hee with me.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>CANT. 2.15.</bibl>
               <p>Take vs the foxes, the little foxes which deſtroy the vines; for our vines haue ſmall grapes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Anno 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:728:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:728:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The preface of the author.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ere it not (gentle reader) that the truth of the cauſe, &amp; the want in the practiſe, had a long time called vnto me, in reading of Gods book, and by experience of former time, drawing out before me, in the dayly knowledge of my conſcience, the manifold neceſſitye of Chriſts diſcipline: I would not haue aduentured, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine own wants, to put pen to the paper in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſo great waight. But knowing that by this my motion, ther might be occaſion to the learned &amp; wiſe, to think vpon very good things for the benefite of this realme, &amp; (if need be) to ſet forth more deepe &amp; ſetled demonſtration, with far more exceding excellency: &amp; for that I ſee the wiles of Sathan, by works of diſgrace to hinder the good of my country: I thought it my duty to our high God, to his holy church, the Queens moſt excellent Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>, &amp; my natiue cuntrie, by ſuch meanes as theſe troubleſome times would giue me leaue, vnto my louing mother that bare me, &amp; my tender nurſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fedeth me, thoſe good &amp; honeſt fruites wherwith God hath vouchſaued me for hir vſe: beſeeching al my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing cuntrimen, charitably, ſoberly &amp; wiſely to think &amp; with ſanctified affections to deale in theſe matters: that the hand of our God may bee with vs, to giue vs this honor, that at the length his cauſe may haue fauor and preuaile to the profit &amp; ioy of vs &amp; our poſteritie. And I deſire no other good wil of thee (gentle reader) whoſoeuer thou be, in the chriſtian accepting of this worke, than my very ſoule, in doing hereof, did with great care &amp; godly loue ſeeke the proſperous eſtate of this land, &amp; the flouriſhing of Gods church: for whoſe peace let vs pray night and day.</p>
            <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:728:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN I had read ouer this treatiſe (which by the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God light into my handes) and conſidered not onely the declaration of Chriſtes diſcipline in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof, though briefly, yet plainely ſet down, and plentifully proued by thoſe teſtimonies of Scripture, that (after many aſſaults) doth confirme the cauſe vnanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably but alſo the aequity, eaſines, the benefit and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity thereof euen in reaſon and policy, for the ſafty of hir Maieſty, the peace of the Land, the rooting out of popery and al other vngodlines; and that by ſuch reaſons as anſwere the fooliſh obiections of ignorant politikes: and in ſuch maner layde open and vrged, as may ſatisfy al that bee not be ſotted with wilful ignorance, and ſturre the turbulent affection of none: as I took juſt occaſion to praiſe God for his labors, whoſoeuer was the penner of it: ſo did it giue me matter to encreaſe my perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that which long before I had conceaued, to wit that the Lorde meaneth certainlye either to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh this ſame ſcepter of his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus in a glorious manner among vs, or to make England an example of his vengeance for the reiecting of it. For firſt it is euident that God hath cleared it ſo euidently, &amp; that by ſo dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and ſundry ſorts of handling the ſame, as no man of what ſtate ſoeuer (if he deſire to know it,) can want wherwith to ſatisfy his expectation. For if thou deſire to haue it diſputed againſt a profeſſed and bitter enemy ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, thou haſt the firſt and ſecond reply of T. C. againſt D. VV. If thou wouldſt heare it handled in a ſweet and pleaſant latine ſtyle, the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſcipline is able to content thee, if thou be vnlearned &amp; deſire the ſame courſe in thy mother tongue, beholde the Learned diſcourſe (whiche D. Bridges aſſaying to confute hath confirmed) the ſermon vpon Rom. 12. &amp;c. If thou deſire to ſee it layd open and concluded in ſcholaſtical manner, the demonſtration doeth that way ſatisfy thee and laſtly, if thou wouldſt ſee it freed from the ſclander that are againſt it, anſwere the obiections that may be, and are coyned to diſgrace it, and vnderſtand how it ouerturneth not, neither (in the ſubſtance) altereth any tollerable common-wealth; but is the onely ſtay and prop of euery good policy: beſides the forenamed, and many other worthye writings, this preſent treatiſe profeſſeth &amp; notablye performeth the ſame: ſo that there is no man, learned or vnlearned, feruent or myld, imployed or at leaſure, but God hath prepared ſome of theſe books (except he be as the deafe adder) euery way to iuſtify the truth of his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline vnto him: which cauſeth me to gather vnto my ſelf a comfortable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that theſe ſeueral guiftes, beſtowed vpon diuers men, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted vnto the Church in ſo diuers a manner, and al to one end; are not in vaine: But for the great good and comfort of thoſe that ſhal ſtriue for this cauſe in this age, and for their certane direction that ſhall reap the benefite of it, in the ages to come. But (alas) if we diligently wey on the other ſide, how this glorious and heauenly offer of the Lord vnto vs hath beene and is reiectcd, and ſhamfully diſgraced by al eſtates and conditions. How greate ones caſt of the yoak &amp; break the bands: yea, &amp; how that many who ſhould haue commended the ſame vnto the prince with Helkijah, haue imploied al their wit and learning to traduce it with Amaſiah yea and ſpent al their time in converting, ſclaundering, diſplacing &amp; impryſoning thoſe that haue bene but ſuſpected to fauor this truth: &amp; laſtlye when the increaſe of Gods diſhonour that ary ſeth from hence is dulie weyed, it giueth vs rather cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:728:3"/>to feare, that God hath cleared his own light thus manifeſtly vnto vs, rather to make vs the more without excuſe, than to make vs pertakers of ſo heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a condition. For we ſee how it commeth, that our great Cleargye may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſpend al their time, in vexing of Gods people, and ſet themſelues to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſgrace all that fauor this way: the miniſters of God that ſhould be alwayes buſied in ſtudying Gods word, and teaching their people, ar conſtrained to ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the moſt of their tyme, in ſeeking to be quite of thoſe intollerable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtations wherwith they ar daily vexed: the nobles &amp; gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hereby to doe what they liſt: and the people ſeing the miniſters in ſuch disgrace, care not a button for their doctrine, ſo that if any of them bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued for their ſinnes, they can be thus reuenged, complain of him to the Biſhop that he is a miſlyker of the ſtate of L. Biſhops: and they are ſo jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of their honor, that they admit the information of knowne Papiſtes, or any other notorious wicked wretches, &amp; wil (yea do vſually) giue more countenance to the verieſt varlet in the Land that commeth with ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plaint; than to the moſt learned miniſter in al their dioceſe, if he be thought to lyke of the diſcipline, and (which is the greater argument of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance not far off) ignorance and contempt of Gods word, and al kinde of ſinne aboundeth in euery place, and in al eſtates and conditions: ſo that as the conſideration of Gods mercies towards vs in offering vs this bleſſing, giueth vs ſome cauſe to truſt that he wil perfect his good worke begun in this Land: ſo the regard of the encreaſe of al kindes of monſtrous tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions doth juſtly occaſion vs to fear that the land hath prepared (whiche without ſpeedy reformation we ſhal ſhortly feele) ſuch a ſcourge as ſhal mak vs more wondered at for our puniſhment, then wee haue bene admired for our peace: yet may none of theſe things diſcourage the ſeekers of this holye Reformation, for if they look to be crowned, they muſt ſtryue to the end. And let the aduerſaries of the ſame know, that it may be their wickedneſſe ſhal being thus much to paſſe, as to keep it from vs for a tyme: but if they think either to weary the defenders, or leſſen their nomber, or ouerthrow the cauſe: the miſtres of fooles, their owne experience doth ſhew them that they deceaue themſelues. For is not the cauſe far more cleared, and the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them that fauor and ſeeke to aduance it, ſince they haue waged war againſt it vnder their laſt general, mightely multiplied aboue that which was to be ſene before? Yes doutles, &amp; ſo it muſt be ſtil: for it being a portion of the Goſpel, muſt needs be of the nature of the Goſpel, even to ſpring wher it is cut down, and to ſpread where it is troden vpon: and though the loue of Egipt cauſe this generation never to know what ſo heauenly a conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meaneth, yea and Moſes his ill managing of the matter be the cauſe that he ſhal onely ſee it: yet certainly the dayes wil come, when our poſterity ſhal no more be gainſaid for deſiring &amp; practiſing Chriſts diſcipline, (for which we ar ſo many wayes abuſed) then we ar for profeſſing of the doctrine, for which our fathers ſhed their blood. Let this be the concluſion of al, thogh the Lord do not vouchſafe this generation an honor ſo excellent, yet take thou heed that thou be no meanes of keeping it back: for if thou be a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, &amp; giue thy hart, hand or countenance againſt it; if a magiſtrate, &amp; do any way diſcountenance it, if a priuat perſon, &amp; ceaſe to pray for it or liue a life vnworthy of it: thou ſhalt anſwere at the day of judgement, &amp; be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted as an enemye to the kingdome of Chriſt Ieſus, and an occaſion that in thy time be raigned not over that generation: &amp; therefore by this book &amp; ſuch others informe thy ſelfe in the trueth of it: &amp; when thou knoweſt it, be in loue with it &amp; ſo labour by al the meanes of thy calling to aduaunce it: ſo ſhalt thou be comforted whether with it, or without it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:728:4"/>
            <head>AN HVMBLE MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION VVITH SVBMISSION TO THE Ll. OF THE COVNSELL CONCERNING THE NECESSITY of Chriſts diſcipline in our Land.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HO ſo calleth to minde the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eſtate of this land, before the happye entrance of the gracious raygne of our deare Soueraigne, Queene Elizabeth, (whom God long continue &amp; preſerue,) in what ſort the forrain and vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped power of the Romiſh Antichriſt, was injurious to the common-wealth, and cruell to the true members of Chriſts church: and compare it with the joyfull li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and godly tranquillity of all ſortes and degrees of people, in the midſt of ſo many moſt apparant dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, moſt mildlye and ſweetly begunne, and through ſo ſtrange, ſo ſecrete, ſo mighty, ſo continual, miſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and monſtrous platformes, conſtantly &amp; firmely ſeated and eſtabliſhed: he ſhall ſee great cauſe that we Engliſhmen haue, both to admire the wonderful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of our mercifull God, &amp; to magnify the high glory of his vaſpeakeable goodnes; not onelye for his rich bleſſings both heauenly and earthly, with aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of peace: but alſo for his rare kindnes of great long ſuffering and miraculous deliuerance. Surely we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:728:4"/>may be truly ſaid to be the vineyard of the Lord,<note place="margin">Eſay. 5.</note> and his pleaſant plante ſet in the fruitfull hill, dreſſed and fenſed by God himſelf. And this hath hee done this thirtie yeare, looking we ſhould haue brought foorth fruit accordingly. Now I would to God that it were not true of vs, as of Iſrael, that God looked for judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; behold a leaper fore, for righteouſnes but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a crying. Many good lawes for maintaining of a quiet and dutifull ciuill life, are very wiſely &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently prouided; I pray God it bee notlaide to our charge, that they are negligently and corruptly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: yea, the aboundance of ſutes, quarrels, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints appeales, preſentments, indightments and ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions do argue apparantly the cruelty, extortion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, deceit, oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, murders, thefts, whordoms, and manye other ſtrange villanies wherewith the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull people of this land be guilty. And how ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, lying, idlenes, drunkennes, exceſſe of meat, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes, exceſſe by pryde, and an vnmerciful and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning gripping of the poore by many ſtrange reatches, &amp; Machiauelian plottes, ar left almoſt without check or controlement, it grieueth them who weep ouer Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and maketh good men to feare very much, ſeeing that for theſe things God hath puniſhed many people and caſte off them that were moſte neereſt and deareſt vnto him, as it is written:<note place="margin">Hierem. 7. Ezech. 16.</note> for the tranſgreſſion of the land there are many princes thereof. And againe, hee turneth the floodes into a wildernes,<note place="margin">Hoſea 4.1. Proverb. 28.2. Pſal. 107.33.</note> and the ſpringes of water into drynes, and a fruitfull lande into barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for the wickednes of them that dwel therin. This latter we haue felt in ſome ſort of late, whiche mighte make vs to ſuſpect our own wretchednes: and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (which the Lord in mercy kepe far from vs,) hath
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:728:5"/>beene wonderfullye in the great pacience and tender compaſſion of God, and yet not without many feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full threatnings hitherto preuented, and (as it were) waiting our conuerſion, put off and prolongued: god giue euery Engliſh man the grace to ſee it.</p>
            <p>But look we into the Churches among vs (oh that the nakednes thereof is ſo open,) ſhall wee not finde there,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.10. Ioh. 3.9.</note> Demas embracing this preſent world, Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes louing preheminence, to caſt out the brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do better than himſelf,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.6.</note> the Scribes and the Phariſies, making the commandement of God of no authoritye by their traditions:<note place="margin">Mat. 21.12.</note> buyers and ſellers &amp; money chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in the temple? Shall wee not finde there blynde watch men that haue no knowledge,<note place="margin">Eſa. 56.10.</note> dumb dogs that cannot bark, they ly and ſleep, and delyte in ſleeping, euen greedy dogs that can neuer haue enough.<note place="margin">Amos 7.10.</note> Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah the Prieſt complaineth againſt Amos the prophet and the prophets which deceaue the people, byte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with their teeth and cry peace. Shal we not finde that by theſe,<note place="margin">Micha. 3.5. &amp; 6.16.</note> ſome of the ſtatuts of Omri, and of the maner of the houſe of Ahab, are kept and maintained, even the marks of the ſecond beaſt,<note place="margin">Reu. 13.11.16</note> which commeth out of the earth? How can theſe things become the holye Churches of Chriſt, and yet we doe thinke our ſelues riche, increaſed with goods, and to haue neede of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: not knowing our wretchednes, miſery, pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, blindnes and nakednes. I praye God it befall not vs, (as was threatned vnto the Angell of the Church of the Laodiceans) that becauſe we ar neither hot nor colde,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.14.15.</note> the high-prieſt of our profeſſion Ieſus Chriſte, ſpew vs out of his mouth. Heere we ſee the exceding riches of the bountifulnes, pacience, and long fuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of God, leading vs to repentance: and our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:728:5"/>&amp; diſobedience, giuing occaſion of the altering of Gods mercye and our happines. What is then to be done? Salomon anſwereth very wiſely:<note place="margin">Prov. 22.3.</note> A prudent man ſeeth the plague, &amp; hydeth himſelf, but the fooliſh go on ſtill &amp; ar puniſhed. And again,<note place="margin">Cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.32.</note> Eaſe ſlayeth the fooliſh, &amp; the proſperity of fooles deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, Very ſober and wiſe were thoſe prieſts, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, chiefe fathers, and auncient men, who having ſeene the firſt temple of Salomon, wept in the daies of Ezra, when they ſawe the foundation of the Temple,<note place="margin">Ezra. 3.12.</note> which was after the captiuity of Babilon, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that many others ſhouted aloud for joy. And in the time of Nehemiah, the people in the daye of their joyfull ſolemnitye, wept and mourned,<note place="margin">Nehem. 8. &amp; 9. &amp; 10.</note> and with one conſent joyned vnto their feaſt, wherein they covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with God to amend their liues, and make ſtatuts for themſelues to follow his Law. So I am verely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that many graue and prudent Chriſtians haue their reioicing mixed with griefe, when the want of things yet not attained vnto, maketh them to feele the leſſe comfort in that which they haue, and the feare of Gods anger for the abuſe of that which we poſſeſſe, &amp; for the refuſing of other more graces offered, doeth daunt their courage; while other men think all is well, and follow the pleaſures of their hartes: and this is of all other moſte lamentable, that neither mercye nor threatnings, corrections nor comforts, feares nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerances, though the warnings of God bee neuer ſo apparant, can yet moue our hartes to goe one degree forward in the reedifiing of the decaied places of gods churches, but we ſay with the people in the dayes of the Prophet Haggai. The tyme is not yet come,<note place="margin">Haggea. 1.2.</note> that the Lords houſe ſhould be built: but wee marke not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:728:6"/>what God ſaieth againe:<note place="margin">The reaſon of this booke</note> Is it time for your ſelues to dwell in your ſeeled hou2es, &amp; this houſe lye waſte: Conſider your owne waies in your heartes, you haue ſowen much, and bring in little, &amp;c. you looked for much, and lo it came to little: and when you brought it home, I did blow vpon it, and why ſaith the Lorde of hoſtes? becauſe of my houſe that is waſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe (Right H.) I haue taken in hande this treatiſe, that I might ſhew a way for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of our happy eſtate, which I take to be, by eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhing the church government according to Gods a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, by which al the former enormities, and al other being taken away, the glory of God may floriſh the more among vs, the honour of hir Maieſtye more highly advanced, and by the favor of God our ioyes may be exalted. Which work as an humble motion, I do with all duetifull ſubmiſſion preſent vnto your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable wiſdomes, deſiring no further to be eſteemed herein, than the deuine wiſdom of Gods word which cannot erre, &amp; good reaſon (not contrary to the ſame) do warrant that which I ſay, and perſwade that which I ſpeake.</p>
            <p>The propoſition which I take in hande to proue is this:<note place="margin">The Propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> It is the beſt and ſureſt policy for the maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of peace, &amp; the good eſtate of this land every way, to reforme the diſorders of the church according to the holy Scriptures of God, and to haue no other church-government, than that which Chriſt hath ordained &amp; the apoſtles practiſed. The reaſon why I frame my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after this order, to mak it a matter of very good policye to ſet vp diſcipline in England according to gods word ariſeth vpon this: that I heare in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and lately haue read publikelye ſet forth, as à de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:728:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of L. Bb. that it is eſteemed (by the abuſe of the true rules of policy) to bee dangerous to the ſtate,<note place="margin">no invectiue.</note> full of many inconveniences, &amp; not fit, yea vnpoſſible for a maine country or region as ours is. Which when I conſidered to be in reaſon and truth far otherwiſe, and that the vnſeated wiſedome of mens frailty and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance do greatly ſtumble at it, I thought it my duty to God, to hit Majeſty, and my natiue country to vnfold the ſecrete meditations and obſervations of my hart: which as I ſubmit to the conſideration of the wiſeand godly learned, ſo I referre it wholly to the maiſter of the houſe (which is a God of knowledge,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.3.</note> by whome enterpriſes do come to paſſe) to giue that ſucces which his good pleaſure thinketh beſt.</p>
            <p>In the next place my humble deſire is, that this my propoſition and whole treatiſe, be vnderſtood, not as any invectine againſt the preſent ſtate, or that either I diſanulled the churches of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be the churches of God,<note place="margin">Churches of England true viſible churches</note> or that the true doctrine of the goſpell were not preached, or the true ſacramentes adminiſtred, which ar the infallible tokens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true viſible church: but that certaine things of very good moment for the due and right adminiſtration of the church &amp; the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinges thereof (whereof God hath lefte as ſtraight commandement as for the reſt) haue not yet obtained their due authoritye, but for lacke of that good enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment which God looketh for of his churches, may argue a change and a ſmal continuance of our preſent welfare.</p>
            <p>After this I pray that my meaning may be knowne touching the diſorders of the church: that I tak them to be of two ſortes: namely, of Ceremonies which ar variable according to time, place, &amp; occaſions, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:728:7"/>come vnder this generall rule,<note place="margin">Diſorders</note> 
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> Let all things be done honeſtly and orderly. Whereby the church is autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to conſider and ordaine in ſmal matters, not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly determined in the worde, touching the tyme &amp; manner of doing ſuch or ſuch a thing, which thing is preſcribed in the worde, that there be no confuſion or vnſeemlines in the time and manner of doing. The other ſort of diſorders whereof I eſpecially ſpeake &amp; meane to ſtande in, is a thing of greater importance: namely, where the church preſumeth to adde, dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh or take away any of thoſe things which God hath ordained to be obſerued, or to bring in other of their owne, whereof God hath giuen hir no authoritye by his word: as in the adminiſtrations, giftes, and works of the church: that where 1. Cor. 12. the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are vnder one Lord, the giftes of one ſpirit, &amp; the workes of one God: if the church do take vpon hir to make new adminiſtrations, apointing vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giftes and works, wherof the Lord, the ſpirit, and god haue made no aſſignment to hir, that this is a great diſorder: and ſo I vnderſtand the church governement or diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, not to be in ſmall and trifling ceremonies, (ſuch as are howres, places, garmentes, ſeates, tables, &amp;c. which yet in their kindes are neceſſary, being ordered after the former rule of comelines and order:) but in the very ſwaye and frame of the churche, the pillars, foundations,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9.10.</note> building and builders thereof: as the king which is Chriſt, his officers, their offices &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion with their callings, abdications, continuance, giftes, workes, and prerogatiues: for the good ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and laying together of each ſtone,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.4.5.6. Kom. 9.5.</note> and rearing vp the whole forme and beauty of the temple of God, ac cording to the pattern given, not by the ſervant, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:728:7"/>by the ſonne who is ouer the houſe,<note place="margin">of two ſortes.</note> and whoſe houſe euery church is, and who is over all, God bleſſed for ever. Amen.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place that I ſay no other governement of the church ought to be ſuffered but that which Chriſt hath ordained, &amp;c. although by many men the ſame hath beene learnedly and truly deſcribed, yet becauſe it is the thing wherwith only in all this treatiſe I binde my ſelfe to medle, I will briefly ſet foorth a ſmall and plaine patterne thereof (as it were in a card lightly.) Leauing the reader to other books already extant, for the larger diſcourſe, and ample confirmation: as by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident and cleare places of ſcripture, God ſhall make me able to ſhew. Firſt this is called (Taxis) order,<note place="margin">Col. 2.5.</note> to which ſoundnes of faith, in Chriſt being joyned, the churches of god ar highly comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, as thoſe which having the foundation layd, are to walk in Chriſt after the manner of the ſame, rooted and built in him,<note place="margin">Diſciplin what.</note> and confirmed in the faith. It is alſo for the manner ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, compared vnto a body,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.4. Ephe. 4.15.16.</note> where the head is joined to the body, and al the members receauing nouriſhment from it, do grow by joints and bands into the head, &amp; one into an other, where every member hath his ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall action. The head heere is Chriſt, the body ar the churches, the members are the people of all ſortes in the churches, hauing ſeverall callings, gifts &amp; works. as it is ſaid: You are the body of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.27. Epheſ. 4.7.</note> and members euery one for his part: and againe, Vnto euery one of vs is given grace according to the meaſure of the gifte of Chriſt. Now as a body haviug all his members vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one head ſeated in their proper places, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſeverall faculties doth bring forth in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the proper action for the good of the whole;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:728:8"/>is a goodly and well ordered bodie:<note place="margin">Diſcipline deſcribed</note> So the members of the church by the ſcriptures are ſet in the churche, 1. Cor. 12 28. vnder one head Ieſus Chriſt. Coloſ. 1.18. and haue ſeveral gifts as faculties given according to the will of the ſpirit to aedifie withall. 1. Cor. 12.7.11. and euerye one hath his office accordinglye in his place, either to propheſie or otherwiſe, which he muſt wait vpon: Rom. 12.6. Act. 20.28. 1. Pet. 5.2. and the people are to obey and ſubmit themſelues: Heb. 13.17 Euerye thing being thus conſtituted, ordered and furniſhed, is a well and right gouerned Churche of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now in this government wee may obſerue diuers ſorts of perſons, and their proper workes, in whiche two things the whole policie is contained. For when euerye one doeth his proper workes of his place, the churche is very well guided. Nowe theſe perſons are the maiſter of the houſe, and the houſhold. And heere firſt we ar very reverently and wiſely, to acknowledge the maiſter and chief gouernour,<note place="margin">Chriſt heade of his Church. Gal. 4.4.</note> who is Lord &amp; king, and this is the only ſonne of God made man, who by his wiſe and powerful adminiſtration, ordereth and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſheth his church,<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.1.</note> and defendeth it againſt al ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and till all bee deſtroied, and hee deliuer vp his kingdome to his father in the day of glory,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.24.</note> and ſo the ſcripture ſpeaketh ſaying: Vnto vs a child is borne, &amp; vnto vs a ſonne is given,<note place="margin">Eſay. 9.6.</note> and the government is vpon his ſhoulder, and hee ſhall call his name wonderfull, counſeller, the mighty God, the euerlaſting father, the prince of peace, the increaſe of his gouernment &amp; peace ſhal haue no end: he ſhal ſit vpon the throne of Dauid, and vpon his kingdome to order it, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh it with judgement and iuſtice from hence, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:728:8"/>for euer, &amp;c. Which the Apoſtle interpreting, ſaith,<note place="margin">by Gods word.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.22.</note> that God hath appointed Chriſt ouer all things to be head to the church, which is his body, &amp;c. Moreouer becauſe his kingdome is not of this world. Ioh. 18.36.<note place="margin">Chriſts govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not civill.</note> that is to ſay, after the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of earthly princes, which in compariſon of this governement is called the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man, 1. Pet. 2.13. being in the earth, he tooke vpon him no earthly or ciuill government, but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelf, teaching that Caeſar ought to haue his due, Mat. 22.21. paying tribute voluntarily, Mat. 17 27 and refuſing ſo much as to deuide betwene brethren, making ſuche civill matters pertaine to other iudges, Luk. 12.13.14 and yeelded himſelf to die without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, when by ciuill authority he was wrongfullie judged, Ioh. 19.11.13.14. &amp;c. Hereof it commeth, that the things by which he governeth, are not of the right of any ciuill regiment, being holye and ſpirituall, and his ſervants or officers are not furniſhed with civill po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer or dignity, 2. Cor. 10.3.4. Luk. 22.25. &amp; his throne is, where he ſitteth at the right hand of the maieſtye in the higheſt places. Heb. 1.3.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing he ruleth by in his viſible church,<note place="margin">Gods worde Chriſts ſcepter.</note> is his word, which is a ſcepter of righteouſnes. Pſal. 45.7 even the word of truth which is the goſpell. Col. 1.5. which becauſe it is ſpirituall, is called the ſword of the ſpirit. Epheſ. 6.17. in ſharpnes to exceed any two ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſworde, entring even to the deuiding a ſunder of the ſoule and the ſpirit, and of the iointes and marrow, diſcerning the thoughtes and intents of the hearte, Heb. 4.12. This is the rod of his mouth, and of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, wherewith he ſmyteth the earth, and ſlayeth the wicked. Eſa. 11.4. Pſal. 110.2. and in the electe who beleeue, Tit. 1.1. it caſteth down the imaginations &amp;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:728:9"/>euery high thing that is exalted againſt the knowledge of God,<note place="margin">Diſcipline deſcribed</note> and bringeth into captiuity euery thought to the obedience of Chriſt. 2. Cor. 10.5. beeing the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God vnto ſaluation, Rom. 1.16. and this is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the church a perfite law, Pſal, 19.7. teaching them judgement and equity and euery good path.<note place="margin">Euery good path in Gods word.</note> Pro. 2.9. The ſecond thing be the ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſures of the church adjoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the word, as vengeance ready prepared if anie diſobeye,<note place="margin">The cenſures joined to the word.</note> 2. Cor. 10.6. with 2. Theſ. 3.14. Theſe hath Chriſt given to his churche, as a power to purge out the leven of malitiouſnes, that they may celebrat the Lords feaſt, and ſerue him ſincerely: Mat. 18.17. 1. cor. 5.4.7.8. Theſe cenſures are of two ſorts, according to the party which offendeth, either to heale and reform, or els to cut off for euer. Men are reformed by admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition or ſharper affliction. Admonition is taughte in 1, Theſ. 5.14. Gal. 6.1. 1. Tim. 5.20, Where admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will not ſerue, according to the qualitye of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe and diſpoſition of the perſon, there are two de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in ſeeking his reformation. Firſt ſuſpenſion, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man is cut off from ſome of the holy exerciſes in the fellowſhip of Saints. Mat. 5.23.24. as namely the lords table, 1. Cor. 11.28. For the greater offenſes and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contumacy followeth excommnnication, whiche is a caſting of them out of the church, and deliuering them to Sathan, in which ſtate they are to bee holden of vs as heathen and publicanes, that is ſuch as ar not of the church. 1. Cor. 5.5. Mat. 18 18. and all theſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their true repentance ar to be forgiuen and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted of the churche, 2. Cor. 2.6. The other cenſure which cutteth off is ſpoken of in 1. Cor. 16.22. If anye man loue not the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, let him bee ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema. [Maranatha] viz. accurſed till the Lord come.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:728:9"/>Wherevpon ſaith Iohn epiſt. 1. cap. 5.16.<note place="margin">by Gods word.</note> There is a ſinne vnto death, I ſay not that thou ſhouldſt pray for it: and Chriſt ſaith, that he which ſpeaketh againſt the holy ghoſt, it ſhal not be forgiuen him, neither in this world, nor in the worlde to come. Mat. 12.32.<note place="margin">The things of Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, not lyke to the things of earthly rulers.</note> Theſe are then far diſtant from the thinges whiche earthlye princes vſe to rule their ſubiectes with: the one med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with the outwarde man, afflicteth the bodye, and thinges of this life: but this toucheth, reformeth, and afflicteth the ſoule, the thoughts, and intentes of the heart: and concerneth the thinges of the lyfe to come.</p>
            <p>In the next place are the other perſons to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered which are vnder Chriſt the king: and theſe are his houſhold, the ſervants and ſubiects of Ieſus Chriſt in his church: according to the dignity of the Lord, &amp; amplitude of his kingdome; are partly ſuperiors,<note place="margin">The ſubiects &amp; officers of chriſt</note> and partly inferiours: the firſt ar ſuch as either haue charge committed vnto them ouer others, as the diſpoſers of the ſecrets of God, 1, Cor. 4.1. or miniſters about the holy things of the church, 1. Tim. 3.13. and the other are all the members of the church, called Saints: who ſubmitting themſelues to the voice of the goſpell, are ſanctified in Chriſt Ieſus. Rom. 1.5.6.7. 1. Cor. 1.2. The duty of theſe latter, is in two words, ſubmiſſion, and obedience. Heb. 13.17. The former are of diuers degrees and ſeverall functions, and therfore require a larger diſcouery, in ſpeaking whereof I bynd my ſelfe to that only which is ordinary and perpetuall. In ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral termes they ar called Biſhops &amp; deacons. Philip. 1.1. The generall termes of their office, bee likewiſe two, propheſie, and a miniſtrie, Rom. 12.6. In deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which diuers offices and officers, the ſcripturs
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:728:10"/>appointeth their calling and workes.<note place="margin">Diſcipline deſcribed</note> 
               <note place="margin">The calling of Chriſts officers</note> In their calling, there is this generall rule, that no man take vpon him this honorable function except he be called. Heb. 5.4. Secondly that there bee a place or charge whereunto there is neede that they ſhould bee called: ſuche was Mathias, Act. 1.20. the Deacons, Act. 6.1.2. the Elders Act. 14.23. Biſhops in Creta, Tit, 1, 5. In their callings, common to all be election and ordination. Election is a free choiſe with the conſent of the people, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is, by impoſition of handes, and prayer: to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to the worke of their calling. Act. 6.2.5.6. 1. Tim. 14.13, Act. 4.23. Vnto this election as a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner this rule is adjoyned, let them firſt be proued, then let them miniſter if they bee founde blameles: 1. Tim. 3.10. that is euery one muſt bee examined be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he be choſen.</p>
            <p>The workes of theſe offices are either proper ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diſtinct nature and gift in their ſeuerall office: or els mixt, wher they joine in ſome common action of the church.<note place="margin">Chriſt hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained diuers officers &amp; their workes.</note> In propheſie, this is peculiar and common to all Biſhops, that they attend vpon the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the word and prayer, Act. 6.4. &amp; theſe Biſhops are of two ſorts, Paſtors and Teachers. Epheſ. 4.11. their giftes diuers, to the one that is Paſtors, is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the word of wiſdome, to the other the worde of knowledge. 1. Cor. 12.8, their works alſo diſtinct, for the former, is to tende on exhortation, and the latter on teaching. Rom. 12.7.8. In the miniſtrye, (that is ſuche offices as haue not to doe with the propheſie or preaching of the word,) there ar governing Elders, &amp; thoſe which properly are called Deacons. The firſte haue their authoritye and title, 1. Cor. 12.28. Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, their gift: 1. Tim. 5.17. to rule well their work,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:728:10"/>Rom. 12.8. a diligent practiſe in ruling.<note place="margin">by Gods words.</note> The deacons are nominated &amp; ſet down what manner of men they ſhould be, 1. Tim. 3.8. their gifts to be full of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt and wiſedome. Act 6.3. their work to looke to the tables, ver. 2. that is, to diſtribute with ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Rom. 12. Vnto theſe are joined widdowes or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the church, whoſe title, gifts, and properties are ſet down Rom, 16.1. 1. Tim. 5.1.2.3.4.5.6. &amp;c. and their worke, Rom. 12.8. to ſhewe mercie with cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
            <p>The mixt worke is of the Paſtors, teachers and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Elders, who are joined in one worke or gifte of ruling well, 1. Tim. 5.17. haue the ſame title of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Act. 14.23. &amp; 20.17. and their worke is joined to looke to themſelues, and the whole flock. ver. 28. and to watche ouer the peoples ſoules. Heb. 13.17. the meeting or aſſembling in this office of governing is called an Elderſhip. 1. Tim. 4.14. And becauſe they beare heerein the power of Chriſt in the church, they are called by excellency of ſpeach, the church. Mat. 18 17. their worke is to ſee all thinges done according to the commandement of God, and ordinance of chriſt. In the callings of the ſeverall offices, and in the vſe of the cenſures that euery man do his duty, as in electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to directe the people, and to examine the partie to be choſen, and to lay their hande, and praye over the party in his ordeining, Act. 6.2.3.6. cap. 14.23. 1. Tim. 4.14. and in the cenſures they haue the ful authority, Mat. 18.17.18.19. except that in ſo great a matter as excommunication, the people haue their intereſt, in that a member is to bee cut off. Therefore that was done in a fuller aſſembly, namely of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole church 1. Cor. 5.4. and the whole church is directed by Paule
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:728:11"/>to receaue ſuch a one againe.<note place="margin">Diſcip. deſcribed by G. word.</note> 2. Cor. 2.6.7. Laſtly, in &amp; about al the former things Chriſt ordained for his church, they haue authority giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to appoint, and ſee that al things be done honeſtly &amp; in order, 1. Cor. 14.40. But if a matter fal out too hard or waighty for one church, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> any maner of waies ſome one church hath need of help: this is ſupplied by other churches. 2. Cor. 8.13.14. When a matter of controucrſie was at Antiochia, they ſent choſen men to Ieruſalem, and there by a greater meeting of the Apoſtles and Elders, the matter being decided: there were alſo choſen men returned with the decrees of that ſynod. Act. 15.1.23. &amp;c. In theſe meetings of ſynods and Elderſhips, ſome one for the time did moderate the aſſembly, not by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtanding office of ſuperiority, but for order to ſee al thinges well and orderly done, and to gather the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion. Such was Peter Act. 1.15. and Iames, Act. 15 13.22. and this is the deſcription of the church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.37. cap. 11.1.2. 1. Tim. 6.14.</note> according to the ſcriptures of God, left &amp; commanded by God to his holy churches for ever: &amp; therefore I take that no other can ſtand with the ſafty of our eſtate.</p>
            <p>They which oppugne this doctrine do not ſimplye denye, that ſuch a thing is taught and commanded in the word, (for it is ſo cleare that no man can but with a ſhameles face, and ſeared conſcience open his mouth to the contrary) but they partly cavill at ſome places, but eſpecially affirme, that it was not commaunded as vnchangeable, that it was of force when the civill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate was not freind, but now it is determinable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diuers eſtats and governments of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: as being not ſo needfull or convenient. Whome I defire in the feare of God to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider theſe few things
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:728:11"/>Firſt,<note place="margin">Chriſts diſcipl. perpetuall.</note> that I haue heere ſhewed it by Gods word (and other haue done it, and can doe a great deale better) if they bring in ſuch an exception, they muſte ſhewe ſome reaſon out of the word for the ſame. For can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which God hath ordained in his worde,<note place="margin">Prouer 30.5.6.</note> be altered by man, without his authoritye whiche or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained it? If God haue ſet Elders to bee gouernors in his church as 1. Cor. 12.28.<note place="margin">Man cannot change Gods precepts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</note> Who that is wiſe will dare to pul them out except he haue commiſſion from him that ſet them there? If the queſtion were touching the officer of an earthly prince, men would keepe ſilence waiting the pleaſure of their ſoveraigne: then muſte it needes bee arrogancy, to deny him whome God hath appointed. Remember them who ſaide, wee will not haue this man to raigne ouer vs. Secundlye,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.24.27</note> conſider this order of Chriſt is not limited to be only when the civill magiſtrate is no freind, and that the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill government ſupplyeth nothing in the roome of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing here ſpoken off: for theſe are (as is ſhewed) for the ſpiritual and heauenly adminiſtration, &amp; theirs is carnall and earthly. And howe can an earthly king thruſte into the houſe of God, an officer, a gifte, or a worke, which he knoweth not whether it will be fitte, or wilbe accepted as agreing with the heuenly pattern Theſe then being plantes which our heauenly father hath not planted ſhalbe rooted vp, &amp; where the feare of God is taught by the precepts of men,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.13.</note> there the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the wiſe ſhall periſh, Eſay. 29.2.13.14. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we haue heard that Chriſt is head vnto the churche in all things, and that princes and judges ſhould learn to be wiſe, and kiſſe the ſonne leaſt he be angry: if the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the churche take vpon hir to alter his ordinance, or a king doe keepe out that which hee commandeth, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:728:12"/>maintaineth other thinges diuers or contrary,<note place="margin">Chriſts diſcipline</note> ar they wiſe and learned? do they kiſſe the ſonne? may they not feare his anger? If it appeare by the goſpell, that all theſe officers are members of the body of Chriſtes church, &amp; are admiſtrations vnder one Lorde; if they haue giftes by one ſpirit, and operations by one God for the aedifiing of the churche: who louing Chriſte, and knowing Chriſt,<note place="margin">Chriſts me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers ought not to be changed.</note> wil readily diſfigure Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, by mangling the members, changing the giftes of the ſpirit, altering the works of God. Againe, if all this be appointed to endnre for the worke of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, to the aedifiing of the body of Chriſt, till we all meete together in the vnity of the faith, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſonne of God, vnto a perfect man, &amp; vnto the meaſure of the age of the fulnes of Chriſt. Epheſ. 4.11.12. And this commandement of church-gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement is to be kept without ſpot, and vnrebukeable vntill the appearing of our Lord Iefus chriſt. 1. Tim 5.21. cap. 6.13.14. then, who is he? or where is he whoſe arme is fleſhe, that will not tremble to ſpeake againſt them? Laſt of al, it is againſt the duty of the church, (who as the pure and chaſt ſpouſe of Chriſt ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be obedient to hir head and lord) to limit the authority,<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.41.</note> and check the wiſedome of hir king: ought ſhe not rather to hearken &amp; conſider, and incline hir eare (being ſwift to heare,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.10. Iames 1.19.</note> and ſlow to ſpeake,) forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting alſo hir owne people &amp; hir fathers houſe: ſo ſhall the king haue pleaſure in hir beauty, for he is hir Lord, and ſhe ought to reverence him. Bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t can this be reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his maieſty,<note place="margin">Chriſts church ought to obey him</note> or taking him to be Lorde: when ſhe ſubmitteth hir ſelfe, to the lawes of gouernement which ſhe hath receaued of his greateſt enimy, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſte, or can ſhe be ſaide to forſake hir fathers houſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:728:12"/>and to hearken:<note place="margin">vnchangeable.</note> who puniſheth &amp; afflicteth as a ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother thoſe hir children, that meeklye putteth hir in minde of the husbande of hir youth, and the oathe of God: detecting and bewraying the filthineſſe of hir skirtes, when ſhe hath defiled hir ſelf with ſtrangers, &amp; ſtandeth ſtifly for the cuſtomes and manners of hir fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, even of vile fleſh and blood, brickle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of blinde men? And who I pray you can ſay (except hee will tell a lye for his mother, and that againſt God his father) that ſhe doth not limit his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and controll his prudencye,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20.</note> when hee giveth hir charge to obſerue all things whatſoever he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded hir, affirming moſt amiably and comfortably vnto hir,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.3.</note> that by his godly power he hath given hir al things that pertaine vnto life and godlines, throughe the knowledge of him that hath called vs vnto glory &amp; vertue, and namely a perfite Law,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7. Prov. 2.9.</note> teaching judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and equity, and euery good path: &amp; yet ſhee leaning to hir owne wiſdome, and preſuming of hir owne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, will alter, adde, diminiſh, and change as ſhe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth beſt. Therfore the Lord moſt earneſtly complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and in the vehemency of his godly iealouſy cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth againſt hir, and ſaith. Ye heauens bee aſtonied at this, be afraied and vtterly confounded ſaith the lord:<note place="margin">Ierem. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for my people haue committed two evils: they haue forſaken mee the fountaine of living waters, to digge them pittes, even broken pittes that can holde no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>In this laſt place, for clearing of my propoſition, &amp; that my reaſons for the policye of our countrey maye plainly be ſeene: I am further to ſhewe in parte, what theſe diſorders be, ſmal or great, and howe neare wee come to the ordinance of Chriſt. Firſt wee holde the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:728:13"/>head Chriſt Ieſus and renounce al other heads of the church, giuing vnto the royall perſon of the Queenes highneſſe, the due and lawfull ſupremacy ouer al per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons within hir dominions, and in all cauſes to vſe the ſworde of juſtice, for the maintenance of well doing, and puniſhing of vice: renouncing all forraine power and potentate to haue any intereſt or title of any ſuche ſupremacy. Secondly, we receaue the ſcepter of chriſt the goſpel of truth, holding and teaching the doctrine of faith &amp; loue according to the ſame: the Sacraments alſo as ſeales of the doctrine in their true nature, are taught &amp; adminiſtred with prayers, ſinging of pſalmes and reading of holy ſcripture: We allow alſo paſtors in every church, and ſome teachers: and by theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteries the word is taught ordinarily in many chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, by meanes whereof the church of England, our mother hath brought forth many notable children to God the father, and notable members of Ieſus Chriſt: Heere one ſteppeth in and ſaith: Is not this wel? you woulde haue bene glad in Queene Maries dayes with leſſe liberty, can you not bee content? Truth, this is well indeed, and I pray God we may bee thankfull as we ought to bee thankfull. Yet as I take it, and they confeſſe, all is not well. And if a man haue the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his houſe laide, and many parts of the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding framed, he will not content himſelf till all be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened together, and the roofe couered. And ſhal we content our ſelues to ſee the houſe of God ful of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and vncouered, becauſe ſome principall parte is well begonne? Let vs then ſee thoſe breaches.</p>
            <p>Surely, ſurely, I would your good Hh. ſhould vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that of all other, I am loatheſt to ſpeake of thoſe thinges: neither would I, if I thought the truth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:728:13"/>of this queſtion might appeare without it: therefore I humbly craue your favorable patience, ſubmitting all that I ſpeake (as before) to your Hh. wiſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not willingly doing anye thing that might giue juſte occaſion of offence. The imperfections of our churches are of two ſortes, either in matter of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, or in thinges ſubſtantiall preſrcibed of God. Of the firſte I will ſay onelye this, that it is well knowen, that ſome of our ceremonies, are part of the character of the beaſt, and therefore not comely for Chriſts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled ſpouſe: but if the other greater things were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, they would fall away of themſelues, lyke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered morter, after a hard froſt. The other, ar ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the holy things, or holy offices. The firſt holy thing is the word, here ſome part of the holy ſcripture is commaunded to be left vnread, the Apocripha are appointed to be read, and that vnder the name of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture, for inſtruction of manners: and homelies in ſteed of preaching: this I take to be an abuſe to the ſcepter of Chriſt, which is before ſhewed to be perfect The other holy things are the cenſures, and namelye excommunication, which is made a ciuill ordinaunce committed to a civill judge in matters of heritage, in a quarrell often groates, for not appearing the partye may be abſolved by his proctour. A miniſters name is vſed in the forme, but he hath nothing to do to judge or determine, or to receaue againe. And beſides all this, the pennance maye bee changed into money or ſome other thing. Heere the Elder-ſhip is deſpiſed, the congregation looſeth hir right, and earth and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven are mingled together: no ſmall disfigure vnto Chriſts church, if you remember howe God woulde haue it ordered and adorned.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:728:14"/>
The diſorders in the holy offices are either by min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling or mangling. Mingling is of two ſorts, firſte the ſuperfluity of offices and officers, as Archbiſhops, L. Biſhops, Chancelors, Commiſſaries, Archdeacons, Officials Deanes, Vicedeanes, Treaſurers of Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall churches, Prebendes, Cannons, Peticannons, Singing men, Quiriſters, Vergers, Curates and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, euery one of theſe haue a certaine dignity aboue others: &amp; beſides that there are Deacons, who haue no charge of the poore at all, Church-wardens, Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and collectors for the poore.<note place="margin">Proverb. 9.3.</note> Are theſe the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens whome wiſdome ſendeth forth to cal the ſimple to hir banquet?<note place="margin">Ver. 1.</note> Are theſe the pillars that God hath ſet in his church?<note place="margin">Eph. 4.8.11.</note> Can it be ſaid that Chriſt when hee aſcended vp on highe, gaue theſe? There is alſo a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond mingling in their workes, as hee that preacheth wil alſo ſit in commiſſion, he wilbe a Paſtor ouer ſome 2. or 3. churches, &amp; an Archdeacon ouer many chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. One man wilbe a Paſtor to one church, a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to an other, and a prebend to an other. In their prayers they ar bound to ſuch a forme as for the moſt part is tranſlated out of the popiſh portues, hauing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers vngodly mixtures of ſignes, with ſacramentall ſignification, as the croſſe in baptiſme, impoſition of handes in confirmation, and of other rites and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations which Gods booke never dreamed of. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all theſe and other ſuch minglings, howe ſhal it be anſwered when the Lorde ſhall ſay, Who requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red theſe things at your hands?<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.12.</note> The manglings ar ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little better. For firſt diuers members are cut off, as governing Elders and Deacons: Preſbyteries of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular churches, and free Synods: In the calling of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters many are made without a place, few haue their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:728:14"/>election with the conſent of the churche: the right of impoſition of handes, is in a L. Biſhop, and ſuche as hee choſeth, manye are made miniſters of the worde that haue no giftes, contrary to the rule in examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In their workes, there wanteth reſidency in many able men: there is no practiſe of preching in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident: fowre ſermons a yeare diſchargeth a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our church. But what ſhould I repeat all? I feare and tremble, that the glorious ſpouſe of Chriſt Ieſus, ſhould thus be defiled with the filthy clouts &amp; rotten patches of the foule &amp; beaſtly ſtrumpet,<note place="margin">Revel. 17.1.9.</note> the whore of Babel, which fitteth on the feven hills of Rome. where is the fulneſſe of Chriſt? Col. 1.9. Where are the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wiſdome and knowledge that are hid in him? cap. 2.13. and howe are wee complete in him? ver. 10. if we ſuffer our ſelues to be led as a pray, through phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and vaine deceat after the traditions of men, and not after Chriſt. ver. 8.</p>
            <p>The queſtion being thus cleared,<note place="margin">Proofer of the propoſition.</note> the reaſons that proue the ſame, will ſhew themſelues more readilye, and be ſene more apparantly. My reaſons are either ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall or ſpeciall- Generally I firſt conſider the author of church-diſcipline, on the one ſide Chriſt furniſhed with authority from God: on the other ſide, mans wiſdome and Antichriſte, aduerſarye againſt GOD, whoſe comming is by the effectuall power of Sathan:<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.4.9. The firſt proofe from the autor of diſcipline.</note> ſeing that it is already ſhewed, that God is the author of that we want, the conſideration of his perſon may teach vs that his is beſte and ſureſt for our eſtate: for he is wonderfull in counſell, and excellent in works, Eſa. 28.29. the fooliſhnes of God is wiſer then men. &amp; the weakenes of God is ſtronger then men, 1. Cor. 2.25. If God tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in counſel be wiſeſt, &amp; in works moſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:728:15"/>perfect &amp; ſtable:<note place="margin">Geueral reaſons ſhewing that Chriſts</note> howe ſhould not all ſtate-men thinke that to reform our churches after his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fell, &amp; to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe his workes were ſafeſt for the eſtate of our lande. Look we vpon ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Antichriſt, &amp; Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what are theſe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> almighty? &amp; their wiſdom to his? Can they teach a church-governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t more certain for our ſafety, than he? Is not the wiſdome of this world fooliſhnes with God? 1. Cor. 3.19. Doth he not take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe in their craf tines, &amp; make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of the wicked fooliſh? Iob. 5.13. And concerning Antichriſt: oght we not to hearke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to him, who calleth vnto vs from heaven, and ſaith: Go out of hir my people,<note place="margin">Revel. 18 4.</note> that ye bee not partakers in hir ſinnes, and that ye receaue not of hir plagues: for hir ſinnes are come vp vnto heauen, and God hath reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bered hir iniquities. As for Sathan, his wiles are but to deceaue, euen as he deceaued Euah, to the miſery of all mankinde: and as hee ſeduced Ahab to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Therefore I think it beſt, and the ſureſt poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to be ruled by God.</p>
            <p>And this reaſon wilbe the more euident,<note place="margin">Our profeſſion is to ſerue God in al he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs.</note> if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our ſelues: what we haue done, and nowe doe. We haue entred into couenant with God, by ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelues to the ſcepter of his word, and taking vpon vs his ſacramentes as badges of our profeſſion. Heere peradventure a wiſe Politian doth not ſee, that it is not ſafe to ſerue two maiſters: though the Lorde ſaith,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.13. 2. Cor. 6.15.</note> You cannot ſerue God &amp; Mammon. And what concord hath Chriſt with Belial.</p>
            <p>The next generall reaſon is from the thing it ſelfe, I meane the church-government which is of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: firſt,<note place="margin">The ſecond ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral reaſon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thing</note> if wee conſider that the ſame being Chriſts, and we chriſtians, what can be better for vs? the ſame is from heauen, heauenly, and ſpirituall: and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:728:15"/>we profeſſe the Lord from heauen,<note place="margin">Diſcip. is for our ſafety.</note> what then can bee ſafer for vs? What do we (fuppoſe you) if wee judge any thing vnfit for vs, when he ſaieth:<note place="margin">Pro. 3.8.</note> All the wordes of my mouth are righteous, there is no lewdneſſe nor frowardnes in them, If the commandement of God by Moſes the ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was ſuch, that no nation was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to Gods people, becauſe no nation had lawes and ordinances ſo righteous, as all that law which hee ſet before them: and if thoſe lawes ſhoulde bee their wiſdome and vnderſtanding before al people:<note place="margin">Deut. 4.6.8.</note> ſo that they which ſhould heare, ſhould be forced to confeſſe only this people is wiſe and of vnderſtanding: Shall we think, that the Lawes of the ſonne, Lord and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the houſe, would make vs leſſe righteous, wiſe,<note place="margin">Chriſts diſcipl. maketh a natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honorable. 1. King. 10.</note> and honorable before al people? If Salomon for the wiſdom which he had of God, was admired &amp; ſought to of all people, &amp; the glory, wealthe, and peace of his kingdome, was herein eſpecially, in that hee builded the materiall temple after the patterne giuen him of God? Is there not a greater than Salomon with vs, and ſhall not the glory of our Queene and countrye, be as great, if we in the building of the ſpirituall tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, vſe no other platforme, but that which God doth ſend vnto vs?</p>
            <p>Ioine herevnto the vſe and end of Chriſts governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: namely, why god appointed Chriſts kingdom: the kings of the earth, and civill ſtates, being ignorant of the myſtery of Chriſts ruling, are many times trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, when they heare that a king is borne:<note place="margin">Mat. 2.1.2.</note> and when they perceaue, that the neuer fay ling worde of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, doth ſet down that it muſt be ſo, where, and how, they lay priuie netts &amp; engines to prevent him: but wiſe men are contrary minded &amp; doe come from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:728:16"/>their owne country,<note place="margin">The end of Chriſts diſcipline</note> to ſeeke him out: &amp; are exceding glad when they ſee the tokens of his comming, reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to do homage before his holy Majeſty, for they know plainly that hee came not to diſſolue the Lawe,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.17.</note> as to teach ſubiectes to diſobey their naturall princes, but to fulfill it: and to make men of conſcience, even without feare of temporall ſword,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.5.</note> to bee ſubiect; and to paye tribute to whome it belongeth. What good ſtate-man that is a chriſtian,<note place="margin">Diſcipline can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hurt the ſtate.</note> can wiſely, and by war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of good policy once dreame, that that manner of governement whiche not medling or vſurping one whit vpon the ciuill power, but by the ſpirituall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfrom Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.18.</note> binding and looſing the ſoule &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, doth ſubdue the will of all euill doers, whiche are ſet againſt the wholſome lawes of God and man, and by the terrour of Sathan doeth make them learne to leaue ſuch euill wayes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.4. 1. Tim. 1.20.</note> that when this is done, as it ought to bee done, and by thoſe perſons and orders, which the ordainer thereof hath appointed: that it ſhoulde hurte the eſtate, and diminiſh the happines of a Chriſtian nation? Therefore well ſaid the Prophet Eſay of this government.<note place="margin">Eſay. 42 4.</note> Hee ſhall not make to ſmok nor bruiſe, till he haue ſet judgement in the earth, and the Yles ſhall wait for his Law. By which he meaneth that the government of Chriſt is ſuch, that of it ſelf in his proper nature, it diſquieteth &amp; troubleth no man, no not to the bruiſing of a reed, or quenching of ſmo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king flaxe: but it peaceably bringeth men to good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, yea, ſaith he, the nations ſhall attend vpon him to be ruled by his Law. See how God hath determined the good of the nations by his ſonnes government: ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it be good policy to refuſe it? And we haue great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of this thing ſince wee ſubmitted our ſelues
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:728:16"/>vnto Chriſt by receauing the goſpell ſo far as we haue done.<note place="margin">to help the civill Magiſt.</note> What works of righteouſnes God hath wroght among vs? Howe is our Queene become an helper of the oppreſſed, and a ſuccour, &amp; a nurſe to the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed? Howe hath our peace vnder hir flouriſhed? What age can ſhewe the lyke in this land? And what praiſe hath God brought vpon this lande, and glorye vnto hir Royall Majeſty, by worſhipping Chriſt, and conſtant defending of his truth? If wee forget all the mighty deliuerances, yet this laſte yeares ouerthrowe of Gods enemies may teſtifie: being ſtrange to all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, admired of all people, an aſtoniſhment to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy; and triumph to the godly: not by power or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, but by the faithfull and mercifull hande of God. Doeth not this (I ſaye) teſtifie:<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.15.</note> Bleſſed is that people that hath the Lord for their God. But if wee haue ſo great profite and pleeaſure by a part of Chriſts gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement: what would it be, if we receaued all? would he not ſay of vs, as he did ſometimes of Sion.<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.14.</note> This is my reſt for euer, heere will I dwell, for I haue a delyte therein: I will ſurely bleſſe hir victuals, and ſatiſſie hir poore with bread: and I wil clothe hir prieſts with ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and hir ſaints ſhall ſhowt for joy. There will I make the horne of Dauid to budde, where I haue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained a light for mine anointed: his enemies will I clothe with ſhame, but on him his crown ſhal floriſh. Looke vpon Iehu king of Iſrael, he was zealous a little,<note place="margin">2. King. 10.30.</note> deſtroing the houſe of wicked Ahab, and the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Baal, &amp; god bleſſed his ſeede to ſit on the thron of Iſrael, vnto the fourth generation: what wold he haue done if hee had bene zealous in all the will of god: but becauſe hee left not the ſinne of leroboam, god loathed Iſraell, and ſmote them in all their coaſts
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:728:17"/>by the ſworde of Haſael. Looke on Aſa alſo king of Iuda,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 14. &amp; cap. 16.</note> when hee ſought the Lord our God, the lande had quietnes ten yeares, and after hee had a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full victory and much ſpoiles of an huge hoſte, often hundreth thouſand and three hundreth charets: but when he made fleſh his arme, and caſt the Seer for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing him into priſon, and oppreſſed certaine of the people, hee had an extreame diſeaſe in his feete in his old dayes, which tooke from him the glory of his youth. Look we farther on that good king Iehoſaphat who cauſed the people to be taught in the law of god, he was wonderfull in peace,<note place="margin">1. Chre. 17. cap 18.1.</note> proſpering in wealth, &amp; maruelous in victory:<note place="margin">Cap. 19.2.</note> yet when hee joined with wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Ahabs houſe, helping the wicked, and loving the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hate the Lord,<note place="margin">Cap. 18.31.</note> did he not hazard his owne life? was not he &amp; his people put in feare with a great mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude from beyond the ſea:<note place="margin">Cap. 20.2.3.37.</note> and were not his ſhippes broken that they were not able to go to Tarſhiſh. And generally from Ioſhua, and thenceforth in all the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Byble, you ſhall hardlye or not at all finde, that ever God bleſſed the people long with peace and proſperitye, when they declined from his Lawes, or that he ſpared good kings, when they followed their owne mindes, and left the will of the Lords word vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>performed. So if we woulde conſider what hath fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the diſorderly and raſh vrging of ſubſcription, (a thing vnder pretence of vnity, to cut the throate of Gods ordinance in diſcipline) when the mouthes of Gods faithfull ſervants were ſtopped, and very many of hir Majeſties moſte faithfull ſubiectes fearing God, grieued and moleſted, it may be it were good policie for vs to beſturre our ſelues to ſet vp reformation: for we know that one feare or plague hath euer ſince fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:728:17"/>an other: firſte in that very yeare, howe manye wayes was hir Majeſties ſacred perſon indangered by the diueliſhe and traiterous Papiſtes, then followed a deare yeare of corne, and after manye were puniſhed with penury: beſides this, we haue ſent forth ſouldiers kept watch &amp; ward, &amp; laſtly forced to forſak al to wait vpon the enimye, whome God brought even in our ſight before our dores, and at this houre wee are ſtill buſie in labour and ſtudy, to keepe the ſworde out of the land. If vnto Iuda and Iſraell ſuch thinges as theſe were warnings, threatnings, and corrections: let vs take heed, that we go not to far in flattering our ſelues moleſting Gods ſervants, refuſing Chriſts ordinance, till it be too late, and there be no remedy. O Lord for chriſts ſake, bow thou our harts, that we may not leane too much, vnto the vncertaine ſtaffe of earthly policy, but looke vnto thee that ſmiteſt vs.</p>
            <p>An other generall reaſon is this,<note place="margin">The thid reaſon from the euent.</note> that now it is eaſie to eſtabliſhe it, and harde to keepe it back: yea ſaith a milde and reverent man: I would gladly know,<note place="margin">D. Some in his treatiſe of decy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding certaine queſt. &amp;c. pa. 36</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee poſſible or ſafe, to plante diſcipline in this land, before that Gods holy truth bee ſoundlye both taught and receaued: and that there be fit church-men and people to execute the diſcipline. I am ſory that by publik authority ſuch a boke ſhould be allowed, that hath no better reaſon againſt diſcipline, then that which ſtandeth with the accuſation of the whole ſtate and diſpraiſe of the whole land. For what can be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhame to our ſtate which profeſſe the true &amp; ſound doctrine of the goſpell, then that the ſame ſhould not be ſoundly taught: and what greater diſpraiſe, then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 30. yeares teaching, there ſhould want fit Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and people, Paule was but one,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.18.19</note> and yet in verie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:728:18"/>few yeares he cauſed the goſpell to abound from Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,<note place="margin">An eaſie matter to ſet vp</note> and rounde about vnto Illiricum:<note place="margin">The Apoſtles in a ſhort time planted very many churches with the diſcipl. of Chriſt.</note> So that hee durſte not ſpeake of any thing, which Chriſt had not wroughte by him, to make the gentiles obedient in word and deede: &amp; we haue diuers L. Biſhops throgh all the ſhieres in England, diſperſed in ſeveral charges, and haue not all they done as much in one countrye, as hee did in many? Hee had the ciuill power againſt him, theſe haue it for them: he was many times trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, impriſoned, theſe haue nothing to feare that might amongeſt men diſcourage them: he was poore and laboured for his liuing diuers times, theſe haue great liuings: he had no humiane help, but the ſimple &amp; ſincere teaching of the truth; theſe haue very large authority: and haue they not yet prevailed ſo farre, as that Gods holy truth, is ſoundly taught and receiued, but that the lacke hereof muſt hinder the good courſe of diſcipline? In a very ſmall time did Pauland Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas preach, and teach, many in Derba, Liſtra, Ico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, and Antiochia:<note place="margin">Act. 13. &amp;. 14.20 21.23.</note> and ordained them Elders in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery church. At Epheſus Paule continued three yeare in whch ſpace he taught them al the counſell of god,<note place="margin">Act. 20, 17.27.28.31.</note> and left them Elders to looke to themſelues and to all the flock. It may be ſome man will object, that Paules calling being extraordinary, and his bleſſing extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, to blame our Bb. may not be fit. I aunſwere, if they will take vpon them an office and charge of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny congregations as Paule, &amp; claime authority in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of churches and church men, as Paule: why ſhould it not bee looked for, that they ſhoulde doe as much good in their place, as he did in his, having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more helpes, then he. But this commeth to paſſe, by no other reaſon, but by the want of Gods church
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:728:18"/>governement.<note place="margin">Diſcipline in England.</note> For when they take a calling whereof they haue no warrant as Paule had, how can they bee bleſſed as Paule: when they meddle with civill cauſes which Paule did not: how can they, or do they attend vnto preching in themſelues, &amp; promote it in others, as Paule did: when they by articles and deuiſed plots make daylie trappes to entangle good preachers, and thruſt many out becauſe they teach all the counſell of God, as Paule did: and maintain, &amp; beare with ſome which preach againſt the counſell of God: and more, which preach neuer a whit of gods counſell, whiche Paule did not: when they haue in their mouthes the waye of preferment, and in their labours the care of honour, and giue diſpenſations to Non-reſidenſy, tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerations to naked Readers, which all were farre from Paule: how can wee look for the fruit of their loyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, which came of his labours: or that ſuch as ſtriue againſt the goſpel, ſhould do good, as he which ſtroue for it. Let all men conſider by this, what it is to bee L.B. (jure humano) by mans lawe, and to bee a poore miniſter and true ſervant of Chriſt, (jure diuino) by gods Law. But it ſhould ſeeme by this queſtion, that if the holy truth of God wer ſoundly taught, &amp;c. then it were poſſible and ſafe to pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t diſcipline in this land, and ſurely I thinke ſo too. But herein I differ, that I am perſwaded that gods truth is ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly taught in this land (which he ſeemeth ſecretlye to denye,<note place="margin">Gods truth is ſoundly taught in England.</note> or elſe his queſtion were no queſtion) and ſo I thinke all men that ſpeake aduiſedly, and all the churches of god will witnes with me: ſo that I think in a matter ſo cleare, I neede not to vſe many vnneceſſary reaſons: therefore it followeth by his own judgement, that it is poſſible and ſafe to plant diſcipline in England, where the holy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:728:19"/>truth of god is ſoundly taught. As touching fit church men and people (god be thanked for it) there be more knowen then be accounted of, and more vnknowen than we are worthy of, and more woulde haue beene if the reſiſting of diſcipline, and maintening of popiſh diſorders, had not diſcouraged ſome, and prevented very many. But I would faine be taught either by the ſcripture of God, or by ſound reaſon; howe in manye places of this Land the holy truth of God, can bee (as it ought) ſoundly taught and receaued, and fit church men and people:<note place="margin">Chriſts orders and diſcipline, maketh fit churchmen and people.</note> till the rule and law of Chriſt be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. For ſee you not, that the orders nowe keepe them out, which would like kynde ſhep-heards feede the flocke, and that it feedeth and foſtereth the Idle &amp; proud Prelacy, who lye lurking in their warme neſts, having manye eaſie impedimentes, and ſweete ſilver coardes to pull them back from their duty, they are ſo inveſted into offices ciuill, and ſo preferred to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the high commiſſion, that their leaſure is ſmal, ſome dwelling in Cathedrall churches, are ſo peſtred with conſultations about leaſes, &amp; changing of church lands, with feaſting and flattering one an other, with rhewmes and ſtitches, and the farnes of the places, or vnholſomnes of the aire, where their charge is: that they commend that buſines to their curate. Some ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving bene put to learne their Catechiſme, &amp; to make exerciſes now thirtie years, are as fitt church-men for knowledge and vtterance, as a childe of eight yeres of age. No marvell then, thoughe the people in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be not ſo fit as they ſhould be: when by the order of our diſorderly church government, ſuch wicked &amp; blinde guides may bee ſuffered and defended. But if according to the law of Chriſts church-governement
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:728:19"/>there were diligent ſearche made in all places of the lande, for wiſe, learned and ſtayed men of all degrees to bee called to the office of Paſtors and teachers: and that by the wiſe circumſpection of theſe, diſcreet and ſober men, with the conſent of ſeveral churches were adjoined as helpers: think you that there woulde bee many places voide of able and godlye teachers. And if there ſhould ſome be, could it long ſo continew, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the power and ſpirituall authoritye of theſe, would ſoone breed ſuch a light, and bring forth ſuch a harveſt, as the beauty and glory of ſuch churches as were eſtabliſhed and furniſhed, would ſoone draw on the other, and cauſe them like wiſe to bee prouided. Now men thruſt in themſelues, then they ſhould be called by other. Nowe men ſeeke (like journey men) a curatſhip, and (like farmers afore hande) get an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowſen before the incumbents leaſe (I ſhould ſay life) be out: then ſhould ſuch as be good men and of fitte giftes be ſought for, not only in the vniverſity, but in the countrie, court cittie, and gentlemen and noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens houſes, wherſoeuer any might be found worthy of ſo high a calling. Now many are violently thruſte out, becauſe they do their duty: then ſhoulde manye be ſet in, who would tremble of themſelues, to enter into that calling, for feare they ſhould not diſcharge it Now many change their ſtudies from diuinity, many after ſtudy go to other trades, many parentes are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged from beſtowing coſte on their children, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſee how little they be eſteemed, if they will not yeelde to the corruption of our diſorders. Then many would change their ſtudies from law, phiſicke, muſick, ſchooling, &amp;c. and many woulde leaue their trades, and parents would think their coſt well beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:728:20"/>&amp; be diuers wayes comforted, to prefer their children to the ſtudy of divinity. Againe, many who now are dumb, if they ſaw Chriſt comming but a fair of with the ſcourge of diſcipline, would ſoone finde their tongues, and the vniting of ſmal pariſhes would make vs need fewer than be: and the ſending of biſh, and non-reſidentes (ſuche I meane as are meete) to a charge, woulde ſupplye ſome that want: and ſome of their curates, (being as learned, as they) woulde ſerue to fill a gappe: and diuers other things would God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, if we would go about it. If the Apoſtles in a ſhort time found fitt men to place for Paſtors, Teachers, El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Deacons in euery church: how much more would it appeare eaſy among vs, if ſo be now after 30. yeares of peace, and increaſe of all kinde of learning, there were liberty for Chriſt; orders, and authority to further the ſame. The worthy example of Iehoſaphat, in this place, might both teach this thing, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage our ſtate men.<note place="margin">2. Chr. 17.6.7.8.9. cap. 14.4.</note> For he firſt ſent teaching Levites throughout all his kingdome to teach the people: and after went through all townes, cauſing them to turne to the Lord. And ſo by little and little in a ſhort time reſtored the church to a wonderfull beautye and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>But it may be the godly reader hearkeneth and lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to know, how I can proue it eaſy at this time to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forme the diſorders in our church, and to plant chriſts diſcipline: hee thinketh peraduenture, that hee ſeeth many things of contrary perſwaſion. Hee that had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the day of the death of Chriſt, ſeing howe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitefully he was handled, would not eaſily haue bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that which Chriſt ſpeaketh Iohn 12.32 I, if I were lift vp from the earth, wil draw al men after me. But if
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:728:20"/>he liuing in the dayes of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantine the great,<note place="margin">Chriſts diſcipl. eaſy to be planted</note> the firſt Chriſtian emperour of Rome, hee had reade ouer the horrible battels of all Potentates by fire and ſworde, for the ſpace of three hundreth yeare againſt Chriſte, he might eaſily ſtand aſtonied to thinke, that through ſo many yeares of vnmeaſurable affliction, ſuch horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tormentes, and infinite butcheries, that the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt ſtood faſt and increaſed, according as it is written: Be thou ruler amidſt thine enemies.<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.14.</note> How much more may wee thinke it eaſie to ſet vp Chriſtes diſcipline in the church, now vnder ſo Chriſtian and milde a Queene, ſo highlye honored of God,<note place="margin">No good thing hard for our gracious Quene.</note> ſo ten derly beloued of hir ſubiects, after ſo many yeares of peace and preaching the Goſpell, vpon ſo good occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as theſe wonderfull warnings and merciful deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances, when thouſandes ſighe for it, and ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands haue ſought it: and approved and worthy men of all ſheires haue conſented vnto it, and in ſome ſorte craved it, and all men almoſt confeſſe that wee ought to haue it (onely they ſay they cannot tell how it may be accompliſhed,) and no man is able ſoundly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute it. In the dayes of King Henry the eight, a prince of noble memory, by the meanes of one man the true right of the King being revealed: how ſoone, &amp; how eaſily was the Popes ſupremacy caſt out of Englande, in a time of great danger, when the Realme had very little acquaintance with the goſpell, and the Pope did rule in mens hearts as God. And without the realm (for the moſt part) the whole world on the contrarye: yet did that worthy King prevaile and keepe his right. King Edward the ſixte, that rare young prince, being tender for yeares, how did he ſet vp the Goſpell in the midſt of darkneſſe? What fitt church-men and people
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:728:21"/>was there, if he had taried till they had come of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, howe long mighte hee haue ſtayed. Or if the Quenes Majeſty had caſt al perils that in reaſon might haue fallen out in reſtoring the churches at hir joifull entraunce into the ſeate of hir rightfull throne: ſhee might haue ſaid it was impoſſible, and not ſafe to alter the ſtate of religion. How much more woulde it bee eaſy now to ouercome and turne out the remnants, &amp; taile of the Pope, when there was no hurt to this land nor great matter in the doing of the thing, to ſubdue &amp; banniſh his head.</p>
            <p>The eaſines of this, may farther appeare if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,<note place="margin">Maintainers of mens traditions deſpiſed.</note> firſt how the maintainers of mens traditions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſts church-gouernment by the juſte judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God,<note place="margin">Malach. 2.4.</note> (as he telleth them in the Propher) are made to be deſpiſed &amp; vile before al people: becauſe they kept not his wayes, but haue beene partiall in the Lawe. So that a poore ſimple miniſter that handleth the worde of God aright, though all his liuing perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture be not worth fourty markes the yeare, is hard with more reverence, &amp; reſorted vnto with more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, than one of thoſe that imagineth that the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of miniſters conſiſteth in outward things, though he haue the great bell rung, and men to helpe him to the pulpit.<note place="margin">Men cty out for lack of teching.</note> Againe, who is ignorant howe men crye out for able miniſters in euery place: what ſutes and ſupplications in time of Parliament, what meanes hath bene made to counſellours?</p>
            <p>In the next place conſider, that the ſame which the L.Bb. and the Cathedrall churches doe poſſeſſe, if it be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in time,<note place="margin">There is liuing for able mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, if it were taken in time.</note> before it be too much ſcambled, how well woulde it ſerue to redeeme impropriations, and augment the ſmaller liuings, and with the ouerplus
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:728:21"/>ſerue to other good vſes, for hir Majeſt. warres, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of learning: how eaſily might two or three, or more ſmall congregations bee vnited into one, when there is law already to do the ſame.</p>
            <p>Againe, ſome of themſelues will ſay in ſome places, that if it pleaſed hir Majeſty they would bee willing, but we muſt not go before a law. But I cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, but they ſlander hir godly &amp; chriſtian minde: for if they would deale faithfully with hir, &amp; by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; by ſuffering others, make this holy trueth of Chriſts Eccleſiaſtical government,<note place="margin">The Queenes Majeſty abuſed by the Bb.</note> plainly knowen to hir royall and princely vnderſtanding: it is impoſſible that ſo zealous and godly a prince, hauing ſo manye yeares in ſo many perils of hir life, againſte ſo manye mighty men abroad, and falſe harts at home, ſo wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; conſtantly maintained the goſpell of Ieſus chriſt, and comfortably receaued ſo many bleſſings, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and aduancements of honor, ſo that hir name is great and terrible to al lands, would be ſo negligent of hir duty, ſo vnthankfull to God, ſo fearefull of any danger, or any way ſo backward: that in hir onely, ſo holy, ſo worthy, ſo hye and neceſſarye a thing, moſte profitable to hir ſubjects, moſt certaine for hir ſafety, ſhould be withſtood &amp; reſiſted. Do not they preach? do they not perſwad? do not they ſue for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions? Do not they ſuſpend, impriſon, and keep back al they can from the courte and Paules croſſe, whiche might detect their vnfaithfulneſſe to God, and abuſing of hir Maieſty.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, if we weigh how the Papiſtes coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are wel alayed, their nets broken, and many fallen into their own pits, and their long woue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpiders web, their filthy plots, by Gods merciful providence made
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:728:22"/>voide,<note place="margin">No hard thing to caſt out</note> &amp; that the zeale of many hath bene lately ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp, and made more deſirous to ſerue God, &amp; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his law: were it not eaſie now to plant diſcipline? and would not all men thinke, that the mercifulnes of God calleth vnto it? and would not his mercies bow thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to like of it? how redily did the people leaue their work without all conſtraint, and with very ſmall and ſlight warning in many places, when they kne we that hir highneſſe was deſirous that God ſhoulde bee ſolemnly praiſed of hir people, howe did this pearce the peoples harts towards hit? how much more wold the Lord frame the peoples harts towardes hir, if this noble worke were enterpriſed, and the fruite thereof would be a thouſand fold doubled.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">The Pope in a conſumption.</note> conſider that ſince the time of Luther, the Lord hath breathed vpon the Pope, and ſtroken him in a mervelous conſumption: and that is a ſure worde of propheſy,<note place="margin">3. Theſ 2.8.</note> that by preaching he ſhal be conſumed, and the people of God haue commiſſion to rewarde him,<note place="margin">Renel. 18.16.</note> and giue him double, according to his workes: think you it wilbe a hard thing to caſt out of England, ſome reliques and ſcattered remnantes of the raile of the beaſte, when wee haue experience that theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſies are true, in the great and moſt ſubſtantial fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of his power. Let vs not feare then, as an harde thing, when God and man, heaven and earth, tyme &amp; place do fauor the worke, and warrant good ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>Out of this followeth the ſecond part of my reaſon, for if the Pope muſt conſume, and that by the breathe of Chriſts mouth,<note place="margin">3. Theſ. 2.3.</note> then ſurely Chriſts meaning is, that his owne kingdome ſhall preuaile. This is the ſtone that was cut without handes, that breaketh the image in pieces,<note place="margin">Dan. 2.34.44.45.</note> &amp; maketh the great monarckes of the world
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:728:22"/>lyke the chaffe of the ſommer flowres,<note place="margin">the reliks of Popery.</note> caried by the winde,<note place="margin">Chriſts king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile.</note> where the place cannot be found, and it ſelfe groweth into a great mountaine to fil the whole earth. This is Michaell the great prince that ſtandeth vp for his people, and caſteth out the great dragon.<note place="margin">Dan. 12.1.</note> This is the King of Kings, and Lorde of Lords.<note place="margin">Reuel. 12.9. cap. 19.16.</note> Now ſeing we craue no other governement but his, and his can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee withſtood: let all ſtate-men judge, whether it bee not harde, and contrary to ſafety, to ſtand againſt him. And if we knew what the Prophet meaneth,<note place="margin">Eſay. 49.23.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaieth: that Kings ſhalbe the nurſing fathers of the church, and Queens hir nources, that they ſhal wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with their faces towardes the earth, and licke vp the duſt of hir feet,<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.6.</note> &amp; that Chriſt ſhalbe judge among the heathen. Hee ſhall fill all with deade bodies, and ſmite the head ouer great countries. We might ſoone perceaue that it wil be hard kicking againſt the prick, and as the Apoſtle ſaid to the Corinthians, for ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling themſelues with the table of the Lord, and table of Deuils. So it may be conſidered of vs for mingling the holy things of Chriſt, with the prophane thinges of Antichriſt. Do we provoke the Lord to anger,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.22.</note> are we ſtronger than he?</p>
            <p>When D.W. was made Archb. and ſet forth his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed deuice of ſubſcription,<note place="margin">Subſcription did but trouble the church and commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-wealth</note> it ſeemed as a ſtrong pot of braſſe that would ſoone haue broken in pieces all the power of poore miniſters, and made diſcipline in vtter contempt. But marke what followed by diſtur bing Gods ſervants and many churches, the cauſe of diſcipline is better known and more favored, &amp; their Hh. and Lordly preſumptions, by a contemptible &amp; very baſe and ſtrange meanes, not once dreamed of by a thouſande of gods ſaints, even when their creaſes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:728:23"/>were ſet vp,<note place="margin">To keepe out diſcipline</note> and they began to ſay, all is ours, was ſo daſhed, daunted and taken down, that the more they ſtirre for their owne glory, againſt the glory of God, the more ſhall they fall before the preſence of his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and the glory of his truth. And in them is fulfilled that which the Lorde ſpake againſt Ely, who ſuffered his ſonnes to prophane the holy things of God. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that honour mee I will honour,<note place="margin">1. Sem. 2.30.</note> and they that deſpiſe me, ſhalbe deſpiſed. Alas, what armour had Dauid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Goliah the great, armed with ſpeare, ſhield, and ſworde,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.40.</note> and brigandine, that he made the whole hoſt to feare: had he any more but his ſhepe-heardes ſling with a ſtone, who fighting in a good cauſe, and in the name of the Lord, ſubdued the Philiſtim, and ſmote off his head with his own ſword.<note place="margin">Iudg. 8.5.6.</note> How did the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Succoth, and the men of Penuel diſpiſe Gideon with his ſmall power, refuſing to giue them breade, when he purſued Zcba and Zalumna kings of Midian, yet wee know, that hee had the victory, and they the ſmart of ſuch contempt.</p>
            <p>Let them conſider I praye you, that by that verye meanes which the children of Iacob thoughte to bee rid of Ioſeph, did God bring to paſſe, that which they feared: and a time came wherin they remembred that they had no compaſſion on the teares of their brother It may be remembred,<note place="margin">Booke of mart. pag. 1430. &amp; 1431.</note> what hard dealing was againſt the reverend and godly man, B. Hooper, and howe God made them to ſee their faultes, and to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled that did it. It may be conſidered that Anno do. 1538. there was an injunction by the noble king Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eight, that the byble ſhould be ſet in churches to bee reade of all men: and anno 1540. the 6. articles followed. Theſe two, lyke vnto the arke of God, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:728:23"/>Dagon in the verye temple of Dagon, had their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict,<note place="margin">no eafie matter.</note> but where was the victory? we this day ſee. So can it not be poſſible to keepe out diſcipline, ſeeing we haue the ſcepter of Chriſt, not only read, but prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched among vs? For in the dayes of King Henry, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon fell down vpon his face on the ground before the arke, and his head and hands were cut off in King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards time: he was ſet vp in a patching manner in the dayes of Queene Mary: he hath receaued the ſecond wound by Queene Elizabeth. And I pray God, that by the emrodes ſent from God, thoſe which maintain the ſtomp that remaineth, be not forced with homage and honour to Chriſt, to giue the Arke of God his free paſſage. I would wiſh rather, &amp; I deſire God moſt hartily, (that now they are in a rage, &amp; furniſhed with commiſſion for their priuat reuenge,) the Lord would ſtryk them as he did Paule, when he went with letters to Damaſcus, and make them to ſee their folly,<note place="margin">Acts 9.</note> that by their happy converſion there may bee reſt to the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of England: and that they may bee aedified and walke in the feare of the Lorde, and be multiplied by the comfort of the holy Ghoſt. O if it woulde pleaſe God to giue them grace like good Elders to fal down before him that ſitteth on the throne, and worſhip him that liueth for euer, to caſt away their popiſh crowne,<note place="margin">Reuel. 4.10.</note> and curſed juriſdiction before his throne, and ſuffer not themſelues to bee called Rabbi,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 5.3.4. Heb. 7.26.</note> or lords of Gods heritage, but let Chriſt bee the onely Teacher, chiefe ſhepe-heard, and Archbiſhop, and liue with their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as examples to the flock. Let them conſider the good example of the faithfull and humble ſervant of Chriſt, Iohn the Baptiſt, who gaue Chriſt the honor, (though his owne diſciples repined) to bee the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:728:24"/>and he as a friend ſtood by,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.29.</note> reioicing to heare his voice, and confeſſing this to bee his joy, and to fill him with joye, ſaying: Hee muſt increaſe, but I muſte decreaſe.</p>
            <p>Seing then that God is the author of this Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call diſcipline which we ſeeke,<note place="margin">The end of the general reaſons</note> and that hee is the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, and his workes moſte permanent, and that mans vaine wiſedome, Antichriſt which conſumeth before him, and Sathan the deceauer, bee the inventers and maintainers of diſorders and vſurped authority in the churche: and that we haue covenanted with God in Chriſt, profeſſe his word, renounce Antichriſte, and God accepteth not Iuke-warme goſpellers, and to be worſhipped by peece-meale, ſeing the thing itſelfe is pure, perfect, and full of all goodneſſe, for the peace, wealth and honour of Gods people, and that it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the joy and happines of all nations. Seing that it is eaſy to be done among vs, hauing the goſpel ſoundly taught, and receaued now thirtie yeares, and the head of Antichriſt broken in peeces, in more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous times, and the ſincerity of doctrine is and hath bene among vs ſet vp, maintained, and zealouſly and conſtantly defended by a moſte chriſtian Princeſſe, &amp; that the enemies are in deriſion, the Papiſtes cooled, the people inflamed with zeale, and the occaſion of Gods mercy calleth vs thereunto; and the very tyme of Antichriſtes conſumption, and that there is living ſufficient, and men, and meanes to accompliſh it. And laſtly, ſeeing it is harde, dangerous, and impoſſible to ſtand againſt it: I moſte humblye beſeech, and moue your Hh. to conſider, whether it be not the beſte and ſureſt policy for this realm, that it may continue quiet and happy, to reforme al diſorders in the church, after
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:728:24"/>the ſcriptures of God, and to ſuffer no other church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouernment, but that which Chriſt ordained, and the Apoſtles practiſed.</p>
            <p>The ſpeciall reaſons are nowe to follow,<note place="margin">More ſpeciall proofes of the propoſition, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church or commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-wealth</note> which are ſuch as ſpecially concerne, either the common-wealth or the church, for theſe are two twinnes which are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited together, and remaine diſtinct in euerye nation fearing God, for the double benefite of the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts thereof, whereby God hath that which is his,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note> and Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar that which is his: and ſome are put a parte in the church, for the matters of God, and ſome in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthe haue civill offices for the affaires of the King. When theſe two are rightly ordered,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 19.11.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joyned together, and remaining diſtincte, doe in their ſeverall natures and proper places worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they make a happy ſtate and people. Which two things, if it may appeare that the eſtabliſhing of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline after Gods worde, will bring to paſſe: I hope it wilbe graunted that the true rules of policy will challenge Chriſts church government for this Land, and banniſh the vſurped and Antichriſtian hierarchy.</p>
            <p>In the common-wealthe, there are the perſons and times to be conſidered: the perſons, for the wiſe and vpright executing of Lawes, and the times of peace &amp; warre, or any other calamity, which requyre a diuers kinde of trauaile and providence. Concerning the temporall and common Lawes and ſtatutes of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme,<note place="margin">The civil eſtate and common lawes of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land worthy great commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</note> ſo far as I can ſee, there can be few nations pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before vs, and for the wiſe fore caſt of thinges in the ſway of the common-wealth, both for the main tenance of peace, and ſtrength for warre, as my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is not to meddle with it, ſo I cannot but admire, &amp; giue god thanks for the rare and honorable vertues
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:728:25"/>of wiſedome and magnanimity,<note place="margin">The orders of Chriſt</note> in hir moſt excellent Majeſty, and the conſtant, faithfull, and diligent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence and labour of hir moſt honorable and graue counſellors: praying God alwaies for the bleſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the ſame. The thing which I endeuour, is onely to ſhew how this happy tract of time, vnder ſo wiſe, both lawes and gouernours may be beſt and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt kept and enlarged, either by that church gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is borrowed and left as the ſmoaking taile of Antichriſt, or by the ordering of the churches, after the word of God.</p>
            <p>If wee ſpeake of the perſons in common,<note place="margin">1. ſpecial reaſon for the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; practiſe of good lawes, Chriſts diſcipl is beſt.</note> howe the good and wholſome lawes ſhould take good effecte both in them, and for them: &amp; we conſider the looſe handling of holy things, whiche is in the very nature of the baſtard diſcipline, &amp; the great occaſions which the church governours and church-men haue, to be drawen away from the juſte and due practiſe of their offices, you ſhal eaſily perceaue, that the matter is clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the experience of times paſte: for as touching the worde, when on the one ſide in the moſt places, there wanteth the quickening work of preaching: and on the other ſide, where that worke is, it is hindred with diſpenſations, Totquots, &amp; ciuill dignities: how can the word of God enter into the conſcience of all degrees, as it were neceſſary to breed a conſcience, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Magiſtrates to execute the lawes juſtly, or in the people to obey them faithfully, being ſo little, being ſlightly &amp; ſo vntimely taught. Wheras Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is,<note place="margin">Act. 14.23. Tit. 1.5.6.</note> that euery church be furniſhed with able me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; of good life and diligent teaching,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.3.4.</note> to be as ſouldiers free from all buſines to ſerue their captaine Chriſt, which a thouſand times more effecteth the due executing, &amp;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:728:25"/>practiſe of Lawes wholſome and good.<note place="margin">Maintaine the common lawes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And as touching the cenſures; firſt when they may bee executed for trifles, and then in waighty matters changed for money: thirdly by perſons which in the nature of the thing ought not to meddle with ſuch ho ly matters; and in regarde of diſtance of place cannot deale ſo juſtly as a good man would and ſhould, (for a man though he be letted with ſicknes, or the Queens Majeſties buſines, is excomunicated before the cauſe of his not appearing bee examined.) Verely all theſe things which lye in the very nature of our diſordered government, &amp; not in the corruption of the perſons, make the holy things of God contemned, the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hated and derided. Very hardlye then can anye man be well and ſoundly brought to be a good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, or ſubiect by theſe, wheras Gods order is,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.17. Act. 20.28.1 Pet. 5.2. Gods order ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and good ſubiectes.</note> that the Elderſhip ſhall watch ouer euery congregation or pariſh, and ſo euery mans cauſe may eaſily be known: and that ſhalbee by men of Eccleſiaſticall function, ſet apart onely for the ſame, according to the qualitye of the offence, without change of any cenſure into a ciuil mulct, without reſpect of perſon be duly and truly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed. If you compare theſe together, and judge in the lykelihood of the ſeuerall nature of thinges (for I meddle not with perſons, in whome alwaies ther may be corruption) you ſhall perceaue that the one is like the leaden rule of Lesbos, which wil bend where the partie to be ruled will not bowe, and the other is the blade of a ſhaken ſworde in the hande of the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins, to keep the way of the tree of life. Tell mee then I pray you, which moſt agreeth with policy (if we were deſirous to haue al good lawes duly executed) a thing contemptible and vile, which is far from true juſtice,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:728:26"/>or that which hath power and pearceth the ſoule.<note place="margin">The diſcipl. of Chriſt altereth not</note>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely this may eaſilye bee obſerued, that the moſt part of ſuch as are againſt the orders of god, are a people that delight in licentiouſnes,<note place="margin">VVicked like not Chriſts di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline.</note> which cannot abyde to heare of their ſinne, and hate to be admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. By whiche it is manifeſt, that the other is of no powerfull nature to keepe men in good order, &amp; that which of all other is a very waighty matter, the nature of theſe diſorders is ſuch, that they keep out &amp; thruſt out of the miniſtery, ſuch worthye men as of all other, are knowne moſt diligent and wiſe, in framing the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcience to all good lawes, for executing of juſtice, and practiſe of obedience.<note n="†" place="margin">By T.C. In the admonition to the people of Eng. pag. 77. &amp;c.</note> Heere it is objected, that the whole ſtate of the lawes of this realme wilbee altered, which is a manifeſt vntruth, as al men may ſee, that the church-gouernment intermedleth not in the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall lawes, but onely with ſuch cannons and lawes, as concerne the eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction and orders: &amp; the proofes from the cannon lawe, and ſtate of ciuili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, of tithes and matrimonye, &amp;c. whiche containe but ſome very ſmall parte of the law, doe of themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues convince the contrary. But as for the cannon law, it is no way hurtful, but good for the ſtate of the lawes of this realme, if it were aboliſhed: being (as heerafter wil appeare) not neceſſary but dangerous to the ſtate, and by former ſtatutes already<note n="*" place="margin">Anno 25. H. 8. cap. 19.</note> indighted, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue a dangerous thing already founde guiltye by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wholſom lawes, was neuer inconuenient. As for the maintaining of ciuilians, as the law already maketh no great neceſſity of them,<note place="margin">There is little need of cannon or ciuil law.</note> hauing little other way to ſet them on worke, but by the cannon lawe: if ſuch mens ſtudies were converted an other waye to more profit, in the church and common wealth, little or no
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:728:26"/>loſſe or inconuenience would follow.<note place="margin">the eſtate of lawes eſtabliſhed.</note> As touching tithes, teſtament, and matrimony, judgements of adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, ſlander, &amp;c. if they bee temporall, why ſhoulde not the magiſtrate haue his right to deale with them: and the alteration will not be great, but onelye perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture ſome ſmal addition vnto thoſe lawes and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes which are already prouided, with an increaſe of matter to thoſe courts and offices already eſtabliſhed, whoſe proceſſe and proceding in judgement, will bee no harder to be apointed, then from time to time in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſtatute, that hath bene made, partly in thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; partly in others, ſince the firſt yeare of hir high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes raigne, hath vſually bene accuſtomed. Touching the Iudiciall lawes, that is nothing to the queſtion, for whether theſe thinges be altered or no, it is all one in reſpecte of diſcipline, which intermedleth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and they may be altered if the wiſeſtates of this land ſee it neceſſary, though the diſciplin craue it not: and if they ſhould be altered, the inconvenience can be no greater, than in ſuch caſes is vſual: for Princes re peale and alter ſuch lawes without hurt, as they finde neceſſary to be repealed and altered, or elſe what need ſo many parliaments, and ſo many new Lawes. As for that is alleadged, concerning the lawes whiche main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Queenes ſupremacy. &amp;c. It is a manifeſt ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as is declared plainly in an anſwere to D.<note place="margin">Sect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Bridges preface, intituled, A defence of the godlye miniſters, and ſhall after be ſeene alſo in this treatiſe.<note place="margin">A lamentable abuſe in impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations and patronages.</note> As for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations and patronages, if they confeſſe a lamen table abuſe, then they joine with vs, that there ought to bee amendement. As for the difficultye, it is ra her preſumed, than any way proued, as ſhal appeare after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: and to ſpeake generally to all the reſt, what hurt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:728:27"/>can there now come to go forward in religion,<note place="margin">The diſcipl. of Chriſt altereth not</note> to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and alter a little,<note place="margin">No danger to go forward in religion.</note> ſeeing that when indeede the whole ſtate of lawes were altered, at the entrance of hir Maieſties moſte happy regiment, in time of more danger as is aforeſaid, the Lord gaue a contrary euent and happy bleſſing. And though it ſeeme a matter of great waight, to alter one of the three eſtats, by which the lawes haue ſtood, yet the Lord hath by the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of your honorable wiſdomes, effected more grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and difficult matters than this. Howbeit (as the Lawiars reporte) the L.Bb. are not one of three eſtats in making lawes,<note place="margin">The L.Bb. not one o the three eſtates by which the lavves do ſtand.</note> but are mingled with the Lords of the vpper houſe, whiche Lords are one of the three e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates. For they deſcribe the ſtate and body of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamen, &amp; the members it conſiſteth of, in this order: Namely,<note place="margin">See the L. Diars book or reports An. 36. H. 8. fol 59. b. and An. M. 1. fol. 93.a.</note> that it doth conſiſt firſt of the King as chief: ſecondly, of the Lords as chiefe members of that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: thirdly, of the commons, that is knights, citizens &amp; burgeſſes as the inferiour members, &amp; al this make the body of the Parliament by whiche the lawes doe ſtand. Whereby I gather, that as before the pryde of Antichriſt brought in the L.Bb. to be lords, joined to the lords temporal in the vpper houſe, the laws ſtood by the ſaid three eſtates without them: ſo it maye bee very well at this time, ſeeing they are not an eſtate of themſelues,<note place="margin">Lavves made without L.Bb. Raſtal. tit. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion &amp; premu mire. cap.4.</note> but joined to the eſtate of the lords, and that diuers ſtatutes haue beene made without them. And if their lordly title and dignity were taken away, might there not bee preſent in the Parliament houſe, ſome wiſe and graue miniſters of eſpecial giftes &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſorted out of all the land, to yeald their counſel according to Gods heauenlye lawe, even as the ciuill judges are ready to giue their aduiſe, according to the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:728:27"/>temporall lawe,<note place="margin">the eſtate of lavves eſtablished</note> and for matters of greater difficultye, there might bee a free Synode after the manner of the Convocation houſe, at all times to miniſter further helpe.</p>
            <p>Come we now to the ſeveral ſortes of perſons, they are either ſuperiors or inferiors: and amongſt theſe (as Peter ſaith) the King is the chiefe.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note> Dauid on a tyme was in a hazarde by a mighty Philiſtime,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 23.26,</note> and reſcued by a valiaunt and faithfull captain Abiſhai. To whom his men ſware, that he ſhoulde go out no more to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, leaſt hee quench the light of Iſraell. Theſe men no doubt did knowe that the glory and ſafety of the whole common wealth did depend vpon a good ma giſtrate: who being taken away, as a light quenched,<note place="margin">A good prince is the light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weale-publick.</note> the whole land was lyke to be in great diſtreſſe and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarde, and this verily is alwayes a principle that neuer faileth. When the righteous are in authority,<note place="margin">Pro. 29.2.</note> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple reioice, but when the wicked beare rule the people ſigh. Therefore wee of England are much bound to praiſe God, both for ſo happye a light which hee hath vouchſaued to giue and keepe vnto vs, our moſte ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſoveraigne lady Elizabeth, and for the great and wiſe trauaile of hir honorable counſellers, ſo far as in them lyeth, to prevent all daungers to hir perſon, and performe euery action that may make for hir preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Graunt mee then I beſeech you, your gracious favour, though I bee the leaſte and baſeſt of the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of England, to ſhew my good-will, my hartye deſire and faithfull minde in this thing.<note place="margin">2. ſpecial reaſon</note> For I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that there is nothing that can by any pollicye be deuiſed, comparable for hir ſafety; vnto the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of diſcipline after gods word.<note place="margin">Princes keping Chriſts worde are his friends.</note> For if it be true,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 12.25.</note> that they that do wickedly ſhall periſh with their king
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:728:28"/>and to diſobey Chriſts commandement be ſinne and wickednes,<note place="margin">Diſcipline after Gods word</note> 
               <note place="margin">1. Tim 1.9.10.</note> and he ſaith you are my friends if you doe whatſocuer I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand you:<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.14.</note> then it is a point of great policy that you labour wiſely, to ſet vp Gods orders in his churches, if you deſire the continuall preſervation of our Queene.</p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Good policy to roote out the ſpriggs of pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that he grow no more to hurt the ſtate.</note> in al hiſtorics it is found to be moſt agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to policy, when thou haſt ſubdued thy capitall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, or banniſhed him, to roote out al his friendes, and whatſoeuer may miniſter occaſion of his returne: and in your bookes of policy, you ſhall finde diuers princes for their ſafety, haue both take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away the heads of the men that might haue beene dangerous to their eſtate, and as conveniently (as poſſible they could) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the forme of government. But ſeeing wee haue ſufficient in Gods word,<note place="margin">1. King. 2.26.</note> I wil not lade you with other. Salomon was a wiſe king as euer liued, he vſed this po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licye towardes Adonijah, Ioab, and Shimei: and the text ſaith, after he had ſlaine theſe three, the kingdom was eſtabliſhed in the hande of Salomon. Nowe this king needed not to change the law, becauſe comming to his crowne by lawfull ſucceſſion, he might ſafelye continue the olde. And yet in the matters of God, he went farther then his father, in building the temple, and ſetting foorth the true ſeruice and worſhip of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God therein: which when he ſwarued from, and followed the lawes of the nations rounde about him, which were enemies by nature vnto him, his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate was troubleſome, and his ende not ſo glorious. For this cauſe God gaue his people when they ſhould enter into the lande of Chanaan this lawe, that they ſhould vtterly deſtroy thoſe nations,<note place="margin">Deu. 7.2.3.4. Cap. 12.2.3.</note> make no covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor haue compaſſion of them; nor make any mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:728:28"/>with them: and ſecondly,<note place="margin">is for the Queenes Maieſt, ſafety</note> that they ſhold deſtroy their Idoles, and all monuments of Idolatry, ſo that the very names of ſuch ſhould not be heard of among them. Which when they did not carefully followe, they were pricks in their ſides, and ſnares to their feet,<note place="margin">Iudg. 2.3</note> and greatly to their wo and miſery. So I doe ſeare, and very much beleue, that one great cauſe of many ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and feares, and flights that wee haue bene put vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, commeth by a contrary policy which foſtereth the enemies of hir Maieſty, and giueth occaſion of manie miſchiefes. What made the I urke preuaile againſt the eaſt churches,<note place="margin">Anno 1245.</note> and that he came even to the borders of Germany, even the ſupremacy of the Pope, which is the maine breach of this diſcipline. But when &amp; how was hee ſtayed? even then when Luther had detected the diſorder of the Antichriſtian Prelacy,<note place="margin">Anno 1529.</note> and at Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna where ſerued the value of reſolute Prote ſtantes,<note place="margin">The breach of Chriſts diſcipl. hath ouer throwen many kingdomes, and namely the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main empire,</note> he had his firſt ſtoppe, and a very great ouerthrow: &amp; why prevailed he ſo farr into Hungarye, but onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they which ſhoulde haue given reſcue, as vaſſals to the Pope, were ſo buſy in healing the wound which the triple crowne had receaued in Saxonye: and that they neglected the true duty to their country.<note place="margin">Anno 604.</note> When Phocas to get fauour after the murthering of Mauri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius his Lorde and maiſter, had graunted to the B. of Rome, to be B. of Bb. and head of all Chriſtian chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: did not the authoritye of the Empire decay and the power of the Empire waxe weake euer ſince? haue not the ſeruants benelords ouer their Lord? Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der I pray you what difference there is betweene the B. of Rome vnder the Emperor, to be made chiefe B. of all Bb. in the Empyie: and that the B. of Canter. ſhould be chief, or Archb. Primate and Metropolitan
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:728:29"/>ouer all the Bb. &amp; churches in England.<note place="margin">Diſcipline after Gods word</note> If that were dangerous to the empyre &amp; Emperour, how can this be fafe for England and the Queene thereof? If Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Becket his predeceſſour, coulde wreſtle with the King, who then was Henry the ſecond: peradventure this man (if occaſion were offred) by his place (I ſpeak not of his perſon) might be made ſtrong to doe ſome thing. If king Henry the eight had not beene wiſe &amp; ſtout, it is to bee doubted that the wiles of Stephen Gardiner, &amp; the pride of Cardinall Woolſey (as one of them in diuers things did croſſe him, and the other many wayes ledd him) might haue very greatly enda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered him and his countrey. If you looke on our L. Bb. their Chancelors,<note place="margin">The Bb. ſeas &amp; cathedral dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities with the cannon law, are entiſements to the Queenes deadly enemies.</note> Archdecons, Commiſſaries &amp;c. and joine (that which they work by) the cannon law: What ſhal you finde but that the Pope hath his horſe readye ſadled and brydled, watching but the time to get vp againe. For if Allin that filthy traitor, and ſuch lyke, had not bene ſet on fire with the loue of the Sea of Canterbury, and other lyke places, &amp; that the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons were not ſo fit for popiſh purpoſes, would there not bee a great deale leſſe ſtomacke in thoſe men, to venture their liues, and very vnhand ſome ſitting for the deadly man of ſinne. Theſe ſeas and Cathedrall cloiſters, are fit for their pompous dwellings, and the cannon lawe is the foundation of his throne. What policye can there bee to leaue anye thing in the lande which might either encourage, or entice, or any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes, ſerue, helpe, or ſtrengthen, the greateſt and moſt deadly foe &amp; hoſtile enemy, which hir Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath, or can haue: and howe can wee long hope that our armies ſhall ſtand before our enemies in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell (though for a while God ſpare vs and call vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance)
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:728:29"/>as long as the greedye mindes of many A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chams which luſt after the Babilonitiſh garment,<note place="margin">is for the Queenes Ma. ſafety</note> and the wedge of gold, and the curſed and damned thing of the cannon Law, bee ſuffered and foſtered among vs.</p>
            <p>But let vs goe a little neerer, may wee not ſee that theſe offices are fitt for Papiſtes, whome no reward (if we beleue D. Parry) can make true ſubiects:<note place="margin">Read the booke of his tragedy. Popiſh church-offices, cloakes for the Queens diſſembling friends.</note> may they not be civilians, and doctors of the cannon law? may they not be Chancelors, and L. biſhops chief coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours? may not they in their courtes, nay doe wee not ſee them daily to ſpare and wink at open recuſants and trouble honeſte poore men, and eſpecially thoſe which are readieſt, to detecte and bewraye their diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to hir Maieſty? So the very order and nature of theſe vnnatural diſorders, is againſt the ſafety of hir Maieſtye. For whatſoeuer foſtereth the fitteſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, to obey the bulles in the great day they look for, that muſt needes bee againſt the Queenes Maic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſafety.</p>
            <p>But beſides that before ſaid, there is an other thing in the being of this corrupt church-gouernment: firſt the lack of teaching of youth: ſecondly, by theſe cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured offices a man may haue a popiſh ſchoole-mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, eſpecially if he can ſemble a little: thirdly, when ſome are ſecretlye intiſed and wauereth; who ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue them? the vanity of ſome, and the ignorance of ſo many, (though a fewe no doubt, bee well able and meet) doth ſo driue them back, and make them ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">Chriſts diſcipl. preventeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volters from his Maieſties obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> that hardly can you heare, that by theſe anye bee drawen to their due and true obedience. But on the other ſide, the whole frame of Gods order is cleane another way. Firſt, al the officers and cannons, horſe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:728:30"/>ſadle,<note place="margin">Diſcipline after Gods word</note> and brydle is taken awaye. Secondly, a learned miniſtry, euery way to write obedience in their heart is heere ſeated. And as he that planteth a right &amp; true catholick Papiſt, cannot plant any other, but a traitor in hart &amp; conſcience: ſo he that by preaching frameth a true chriſtian, cannot but frame a true ſubject in hart and conſcience, when the preaching is the right waye to make true Chriſtians, many revolters may bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, which otherwiſe ſwarme and grow into great nombers.</p>
            <p>This ſaieth one,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> By T.C. In the admonition to the people of Eng. pag. 77.</note> is [non cauſa pro cauſa,] a wrong cauſe, that for lacke of preaching the euill of reuolting hath hapned: ſeing it was not ſo, or ſo much in King Edwards dayes, or in the firſte ten yeares of hir Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties raigne, when we had not half ſo much preaching and a thouſande leſſe preachers: but the true cauſe is the euill hart of men, who heare the word of God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, the ſchiſme of the church, and the Diuel ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king occaſion by ſciſme. Whome I meekely deſire to conſider, that the merciful providence of God, might, did, and doth wonderfully ſtay the hearts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when it pleaſeth him, even without &amp; contrary to meanes:<note place="margin">VVant of a learned miniſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry a cauſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting. Prou. 19.2. &amp; 29.18. Rom. 10.14.15</note> yet by al reaſon, ſeing it is written, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowledge the minde is not good, and that the people periſh, where the viſion faileth, and the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie means of God to inſtruct and bring into the way of truth, is the preaching miniſtery, it muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe that the lack heereof is ſome cauſe of their reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and backſliding. For inquire we into all men, and they will anſwere, ſo we did, becauſe ſo we wereledd and taught. And though the wicked hart of man and ſchiſme, and the Diuell be great occaſions, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cauſes of ſuche thinges, yet the power of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:728:30"/>&amp; the due adminiſtration thereof,<note place="margin">is for the Queenes Maieſt. ſafety</note> is the means to preuent and bridle al theſe: as may appeare, in that the preaching is ordained to open the eyes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Act. 26.18.</note> that they may turn from darknes to light, &amp; from the power of Sathan to God. And how can any man in reaſon thinke, that teaching men obedience &amp; truth ſhould not more draw them to obedience and truth, than not teaching. And if God haue ordained it to do it, why ſhould not the want of Gods ordinance bee a cauſe, that it is not done: as it is written, My people is deſtroied for lack of knowledge. And whence is the euill hart of men maintained, and ſchiſme foſtered,<note place="margin">Hoſh. 4.6.</note> &amp; the Diuell occaſioned to worke his will, but hence: namely, that the one is not taught diligently by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and kept in order by diſcipline, and the other are let out at random for lack of them both. For if by Gods order things were ſquared, where were the ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and the dore for the Diuell: where doth the wolf prevaile, but where the ſhepe-heard ſleepeth, and the dogg doth not bark, and why ſhould we pray the lord of the harueſt, to thruſt in labourers into his harueſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.38.</note> if the want of ſuch laborers, could be no cauſe of harm. For tryall heereof, looke on the country and pariſhes where preaching is by a ſtanding miniſtery, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with other, I could name ſome place of two thouſand communicantes, where there is not a ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted papiſt, and hardly ſhall you ſee ſuch a one tary in ſuch a place, except it be in hope, through the popiſh diſorders, to driue away him who is the meanes of the good ſubiects faithfull hartes. Secondly, if there had beene an Elderſhip joined with ſuch a miniſtery, think you that there could haue beene ſo manye ſeduced as there are, and ſo many hanged, drawen and quartered
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:728:31"/>as there are? When the nature of our diſorders doth ſo negligently prouide a remedy, no maruell thoughe the Ieſuites preuaile as they do. Add hereunto, that by theſe diſorders, thoſe men are broughte into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, which haue written moſt for hir Maieſties right and labored with moſt profit, for the increaſe of good harty ſubiects.</p>
            <p>Heere an other ſteppeth foorth and ſaieth, that in ſtead of thoſe you finde fault withall, you would haue a Pope in euery pariſh, and the Queene ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to your Paſtor, and that by the diſcipline, the juſt power of hir royall magnificence ſhalbe abridged, &amp; in that ſenſe ſlaunder vs with the abuſe of the wordes of Eſaye,<note place="margin">Eſay. 49.23.</note> that Kings and Queenes ſhall worſhip with their faces to the earthe, and licke vp the duſte of the churches feete. Firſt conſider, that to be a Pope ouer one Pariſh,<note place="margin">Chriſts diſcipl. diminiſheth not the Queenes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy.</note> is farther from the crowne and power of a kingdom, than an Archb. or L.B. ouer many pariſhes and ſhieres, yea, Metropolitane of all England: And yet the Paſtour hath no Papall authority to doe as hee liſteth, but hath his voyce only as the reſt,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.14. Act. 20.28. 1. Cor. 5.4.</note> and is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Elderſhip. Neither can he excommunicat without the conſent of the churche: but as Peter and Iohn were ſent by the Apoſtles from Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Act. 8.14. &amp; cap. 15.2.22.</note> and Paule and Barnabas from Antiochia, and Iudas &amp; Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las to Antiochia were ſent by the church: ſo euery pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor is ſubject to the churche and cenſure, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, ſaue onely that he hath an office that euerye man cannot haue. Then it is a ſlaunder alſo to ſaye, that we make hir ſubiect to the Paſtor, for whatſoeuer authority any prince can haue ouer their ſubiects, that we giue vnto hir, teaching euery ſoule to bee ſubiecte to the higher power, neither is it to bee feared whiche
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:728:31"/>ſome men dreame of, for we affirme not (as god know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) that the homage that Eſay ſpeaketh of, is of anie ſuch nature, that hir royall crown and dignity ſhoulde bee ſubiect to any man whatſoeuer, but onelye vnto Chriſt, which I am perſwaded hir moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty moſt freely, and of godlye zeale doeth imbrace: Namely, that Ieſus Chriſt the Lord of life, is Lord of Lordes, and King of Kings, and that his lawes are to bee preferred, before all Princes lawes, and that they ought to bee obedient vnto them, and not contrary. Heere of it commeth to paſſe, that hir Maieſtye coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it no ſubiection to kneele down in the preſence of a miniſter in prayer to God, to heare him preach, and admoniſh hir of hir duty, to deliuer to hir as from god the ſacramentes, and by hir royall authoritye to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and enforce all hir ſubiects to doe the like, and in all other things to ſubmit them ſelues to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Chriſt: and in doing this, hir royall Maieſtie doth greatly honour the church, after the meaning of Eſay, who ſpeaketh in a borrowed ſpeech from earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly potentates, to ſhewe the obedience and honour of Princes to Chriſt in the churche, and their care to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance his church. So then, heerin hir highneſſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God after his owne Lawe, and thereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hir ſelf as a member of the church and not head, and reputing Chriſt onely for heade, to whome in all things ſhe giueth homage, and taking hir ſelf only vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him as chiefe governour ouer all hir people, to ſee euery man, aſwel church-officers as others, to do their duty according to Gods law, hauing the lawful ſword to puniſh them that do it not, &amp; to defend their chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in their right, doeth leeſe no one little iote of hir princely ſupremacye,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.2.</note> for ſhe hath the honour of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:728:32"/>building of the Temple with Salomon,<note place="margin">2. Chron 2: 1. Chron. 28.11, 12.39.</note> to ſee by hir royall authority euery thing done according to the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terne of God, and the Prieſts and Leuites to take their courſes as God hath appointed,<note place="margin">2. King. 12.4 8, 9. 2. Chron. 24.4 9.</note> and with Ioaſh to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Prieſtes to looke to the repairing of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to proclaime in hir dominions, that men ſhal do after the law of Moſes, and by hir authoritye with Iehoſaphat to ſet the Prieſtes and Leuites,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 19.8.</note> and of the chief of the families, for the judgement and cauſe of the Lord: &amp; for the eſtabliſhing of hir ſupreame mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence aboue all perſons, the Lorde will giue vnto the harts of al ſorts of people to do hir co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; of the rulers vnder hir, according to the word of the Lord, as he did for the aduancement of the throne of Ezechias:<note place="margin">2. Chro. 30.6.12.16.</note> ſo that by his direction and commiſſion, the Prieſtes and Leuites did ſanctifie themſelues, to ſtand in their places after the manner according to the lawe of Moſes the man of God. Out of all which I gather, that the diſcipline hindreth not, but that by hir ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame authoritye ſhe may compell all the people to keepe the commandement of God, and the miniſters to be, and do, after the law of Chriſt his ſonne. And by hir commiſſion ſhe may haue, as ſhe hath already, rulers and officers in euery ſhire and great towne, as commiſſioners in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, to be as it were, hir eyes, eares, and hands, to hearken after the due and orderly proceedings of the miniſters, Elderſhips, and Synods: to compell them to doe euerye thing after Gods word, by ciuil authority: and if need be, to puniſh them which handle Gods holy thinges out of order, and to force the people to bee obedient vnto the ordinance of Chriſt Ieſus: ſo that ſhe ſtill ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ouer all perſons, in all things ſupreame gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:728:32"/>(and hir ſelf, vnder none, but God in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt) in that full and royall authority, ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, preeminence, ſupremacy &amp; prerogatiue, which the Lawes already eſtabliſhed do nowe giue vnto hir, and hir Maieſties iniunctions, and the articles of the Convocation houſe, &amp; other writings Apologeticall of hir royall authority and ſupreame dignitye, doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and explane. Now I ſay, ſeeing hir highnes doth acknowledge Chriſt to be hir heade, and renounceth the Pope, is it not for hir ſafety, by hir authority to ſet vp that which remaineth of Chriſts moſte holy lawes, and to banniſh all the Popes cannons? May not hir princely minde perceaue it to bee ſo, if ſhe remember that it is ſaid of Chriſt: By me Kings raigne,<note place="margin">Prou. 8.15.16.</note> and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces decree juſtice: by me princes rule, and the nobles and all the judges of the earth.</p>
            <p>An other reaſon may be drawen from the common effectes of the church gouernment. For if it be true,<note place="margin">Chriſts diſcipl. maketh learned and good men, therefore it is beſt for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch or king.</note> that a certaine Politick counſellour gaue to a heathen Emperour, Omnes imperiti &amp; vitioſi, bono Principi ſuſpecti eſſe debent: that a good Prince may ſuſpecte &amp; ſtand in feare of al ignorant and wicked men: then ſeing that both heauen and earth do witneſſe, that our ſoveraigne is a good prince, that church-government which breedeth moſte learned and good men is beſt, and ſureſt for hir ſafety. What our diſorders do breed all the world ſeeth, it maintaineth blinde guides, how can it make a learned people? and howe wicked men doe ſhrowde them ſelues vnder them, this one thing may ſtande in ſtead of many: that partly by colour of Law, they can ſo moleſt a good man that would teach them and make them good, and partly by commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of pennance, licenſes, diſpenſations and tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:728:33"/>any euill man eſpecially if hee be rich, can tell howe to eſcape their ſlender cob-webs well enough, that men are diſcouraged from preſenting or dealing any way againſt wicked men. And let a good miniſter once ſuffer a harlot to be preſented, ſhe is ſo reformed that ſhe wil haue two or three baſtards on in an others neck, doe the miniſter and the pariſh what they can to the contrary. But how ſuch ſhould or might be ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out, with the through preaching of the Goſpel in euery church, &amp; the good vſe of the diſciplin of Chriſt, and knowledge and wiſedome planted in mans heart, it may appeare by this, that for ciuill, wiſe, and good behauiour, compare them which are vnder continual teaching of Paſtors, with them that be further remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, you ſhall finde a great difference. And how can it chooſe but nouriſh learning, when the wiſdome of the word ſhineth in euery church, by a ſtanding Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, and Teacher? Will it not inflame mens heartes, with the bewty thereof? There ſhall you ſee yong &amp; olde called from blindenes to light, from wickedneſſe to vertue and piety: muſt it not needs turne a great ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye more, where it wanteth? Conſider what M. Fox ſaieth of M. Thomas Bilney of Hadley,<note place="margin">Booke of mart. pag. 445.</note> that the ſame churche ſeemed in his time, rather to bee lyke an Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, than a poore towne of clothing. Tel me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Non-reſident, or idle &amp; dumb miniſter can or hath done the lyke? and verely when men know their duties to hir Maieſty, it is the waye to make them doe it: but if they be not taught, how ſhall they know.</p>
            <p>But of all others,<note place="margin">Chriſts diſcipl. an enemy to flat terers, who ſpoile good rulers.</note> I finde that flatterers are reported of ſome to be moſt dangerous to the ſafty of a prince, as in the life of Alexander the great, when hee delte hardly with them that tolde him the truth, &amp; yeelded
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:728:33"/>to flattery, to beare the reputation of lupiters ſonne, he was neuer without one treaſon, or tumult or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in the ende, (as ſome eſteeme) poyſoned. Now the diſorders of our church, what are they, but a very maſſe of flattery, and a pit that caſteth out flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers: for while men contrary to their own knowlege ſay all is well, and there is nothing contrary to Gods word, and that by ſubſcription and other means, they would driue men to allow of euery thing, &amp; that this by order is ſo, that a man were better to ſweare or lie, (which are manifeſt breaches of Gods morall Lawe) then to breake one of theſe traditions, is not this to make vs, not onely ſecure, but to thinke that even the law of God is not comparable to ours. How may this indanger a vertuous Prince; if the Lorde by his grace did not vphold hir? Againe, if it bee ſuſpected that a man doe meane to ſpeake plainly, and truly before hir Maieſty, is there not order prouided by our diſorders and for their maintenance, that if it bee poſſible ſuche ſhall not come in place? Laſtly, thoſe great dignities and ſpirituall promotions may eaſilye beget flatterers. Mee thinketh I ſee a further ſore heere, than I can ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely expreſſe. I praye God to deliuer hir Majeſtie from all flattering, lying, and deceatfull tongues.</p>
            <p>One thing more there is which maketh for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſafety of our noble Lady &amp; miſtreſſe: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that by this meanes when al thinges ſhalbee refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Gods word,<note place="margin">Chriſts diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin furthereth the league with religious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> as it is certain that ſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not haue more hatred than ſhe already hath of the wicked, ſo the Chriſtian princes of al parts wilbe a great deale the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and the league with them the more certaine, and that which is more, many wilbe drawne by hir exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, being a monarch, and a mighty people, to go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:728:34"/>in religion:<note place="margin">Chriſts holy Diſcipline</note> for all wiſe and good potentates, muſt needs think, that this chriſtian Lady and Queen increaſeth much in zeale, wiſedome &amp; courage, and her people growe in the feare of God, and conſtancie in religion: therefore is it our beſt to make much of her and her people, &amp; it is a ſhame for vs if we ſhould not be as forward in zeale, and as valiant in the cauſe of God, as a woman &amp; mayden Queene. Howe much wil theſe and ſuch like thoughts and ſpeches turne to her immortal fame, &amp; preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſafty? for if it were hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to king Ioſias, from age to age, more &amp; more to eſtabliſh religion in the purity thereof: and that Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was noe longer honorable and ſafe, then he kept the ſame rule: howe much more ſhal it be for her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown and ſafety, to deale more wiſely then Solomon the wiſeſt, and to be as zealous as Ioſias, who was for zeale as highly commended as euer any.</p>
            <p>And here fal down two vayne &amp; fond reaſons,<note place="margin">Chriſtes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline no hazard to her majeſtie, nor Argument of inconſtancie if ſhe ſet it vp.</note> that if ſhe ſhoulde reforme the Church, ſhe ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted inconſtant, and purchaſe greater hatred: for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, can there be greater then to ſeeke her life, and to robbe her of her crowne and dignitie? this hath bin ſought after (al the worlde knoweth) by hatred, and can there be greater by diſcipline? al wiſe men wil al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoe thinke that inconſtancie is in going backwarde, &amp; not in going forwarde.<note place="margin">Luk. 14.28.26. Pſal. 84.7. Rom. 1.17.</note> It is inconſtancie to begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>building and not to make an end if one be able: and not to finiſh a good worke well begone is inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, but this is the very nature of a chriſtian, to growe from faith to faith from ſtrength to ſtrength, and from vertue to vertue, that we may appeare before GOD in Sion.</p>
            <p>Concerning the nobillitie and comminaltye of this
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:728:34"/>land,<note place="margin">is good for Nobil. &amp; Com.</note> 
               <note place="margin">The third ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial reaſon.</note> there is a greate cauſe both for the one and the other, to ſeek after diſcipline as God commandeth it: firſt the one leſeth a right in ciuil offices, &amp; functions,<note place="margin">Chriſtes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin giueth the right to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie &amp; comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie.</note> for when it appertaineth not to the eccleſiaſtical func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to medle with workes meere ciuill, as is before declared, then doe they vſurpe vppon the temporall eſtate, to medle with theſe callings, which muſt needs be an injury, and therefore in times paſt (as lawyars ſay) there haue bin diuers lawes made to bridle this inſolencie, and it is a matter puniſhable at the ſeſſions, if they medle with any ſubject,<note place="margin">Maſt. Lambert juſtice of peace booke. 2 cap. 4 pag. 338.</note> to cal him before them or to put him to an oth, otherwiſe then in cauſes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonial, and of reſtament, but if they do not onely beare vppon their ſhoulder the commiſsion of peace and other great commiſsions, but alſo in their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al courts againſt lawe, call her majeſties ſubjects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them in matters which pertain to the ciuil judges, then it doth appeare that ſuch diſorderly gouernment is not to be ſuffered, as a thing plainly injurious to the nobillitie, and comminaltie: beſides, that howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer peraduenture ſome godly Princes haue repoſed greate truſt in ſuch perſons, yet is it a greate diſhonor to the nobilitie and gentillitie of this land, that there coulde not be wiſe and honeſt men ynoughe founde out amongeſt them to deale in ciuil cauſes, but that miniſters muſt be taken from the ſtudye of diuinitye wherwith they ought to beautifie the Church, to the ſtudie of lawe and executing of commiſſions, for they which by the nature of their calling, and manner of bringing vp, they are moſt vnfit.<note place="margin">Chriſts diſcip. affordeth to al ſortes godly &amp; lerned techers.</note> And how can a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man delight in that gouernment, which by the nature thereof, wil take out of his chappel a learned wiſe and zealous miniſter, whome he knoweth to be
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:728:35"/>honeſt and of good conuerſation,<note place="margin">Chriſts holy Diſcipline is good</note> and mainteine in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places ſuch as are cleane otherwiſe, may not al the cominaltie haue litle delight in that diſſipline, which in one yeare coulde ſtop the mouthes of a hundreth godly and faithful preachers, and not in thirty yeares to roote out thirty blinde guides, otherwiſe then na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe and the meere bleſsing of God hath affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?<note place="margin">Chriſtes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline excomu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicateth none for trifles.</note>Can they delight in that which contrary to lawe can cal them for euery trifle, &amp; excommunicat them, which is to deliuer them to the Diuel, if they doe not appeare? I will not here vſe ſuch tearmes which my matter and propoſition requireth, becauſe I ſee the people in their wound, and it is not good to ſtirr and cheriſh an il ſore, but rather to heale it, in as much as God hath appointed an other way. Therefore we lye here at her majeſties feet, crauing, begging, &amp; humbly ſuing, that ſhee woulde looke wel vnto her ſelfe, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the honor of her nobillitie, and haue compaſsion vpon her poore people, who for lack of Chriſtes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſsipline, haue greate cauſe to doubt of her ſafetie, and to feare their own miſerie, and to ſuſpect the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent happines.</p>
            <p>What a godly thing were it,<note place="margin">Chriſtes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline good for children, and moſt equal and juſt for al per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> that the nobility &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaltie had ſome helpe in every place by a learned miniſterie, euen in the infancie of their children, to breede that feare of god, which might preuent worſe matters, which we ſee come to paſſe when the raines are layed looſe in their neckes, and there hath bin litle diſſipline? What a comforte were it that a man might be ſure, no licenſes could ſteale away his daughter, &amp; what eaſe were it for the people, and readines to find out the truth and perfection for juſtice? that in cauſes eccleſiaſtical a man might be cenſured in the Church
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:728:35"/>where he liueth:<note place="margin">for Nobilitie and Commi.</note> the wicked coulde not beare it out with chaunging or perjurye, neither woulde the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent be ſo ſoone oppreſſed (as touching the nature of the thing, I ſpeake not of the perſon) but euery one ſhoulde haue occaſion to be delt withal according to ſight, rightly and honeſtly.</p>
            <p>Now we are to conſider of the times of peace &amp; war, here one ſpeaketh ſoughtly &amp; ſayth,<note place="margin">The 4. ſpeciall reaſon.</note> if your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie ſhoulde ſet vp diſſipline, you ſhoulde haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent rebellion. What might this man haue ſayd vnto Luther, a poore ſimple Fryar,<note place="margin">1518.</note> that ſet vppe the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel almoſt vnder the Alpes of Itallie, which remaineth ſo ſteady, that al the power of princes cannot take it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: and when diuers Popes who ſought his life, and that with ſtrong hand, died, he liued an olde man and ended his dayes peaceably.<note place="margin">No reaſon to feare rebellion by ſetting vp of diſcipline.</note> In the entrance of her highnes gratious raigne, there was more pollicy in reaſon, to haue ſoe objected againſt the ſetting vp of the Goſpel, but nowe God be thanked, the caſe is altered, as I haue before ſhewed, I doe not doubt but that the liuely fayth, which her good &amp; princely hart hath in Chriſt Ieſus, and that royal magnanimitie which ſhe hath alwayes ſhewed, if ſhe might be let to ſee the certaine truth of the venerable doctrine of Chriſts diſcipline, would eaſily perſwade her that ſhe could not doubt, but haue as good ſucceſſe with this, as with the firſt, &amp; the long experience of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and aſſured protection, nowe in a time leſſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, woulde make a matter of ſo great neceſſitie, to be cheerefully ſought for, and ſpedilye put in practiſe. Moſes firſt brought the people out of Egipt, after he declared the lawe, and laſtly erected the tabernacle, ſo I doe not doubt, but as God hath mightely bleſſed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:728:36"/>her in the two firſt,<note place="margin">The Church gouernment of Chriſt</note> hee will as greatly honour her in the laſt.</p>
            <p>But mee thinketh this man in this caſe miſſeth the true rules of pollicie,<note place="margin">The Papiſtes looke for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge ſoe longe as we want Chriſtes holy diſcipline.</note> for where the Papiſts are ſo full of plots, is it not becauſe they are in hope that things will change? and why do they hope? but becauſe they beholde the image of their father the Pope and hys markes: they thinke he is not ſo gone, but that if they did their duty, he might returne. Therefore they are buſie, and many nets are ſpread for the feet of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no cent Princeſſe (whom God bleſſe and maintaine) and engins of diuers forts are made to breake in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our peace. Will you bee without feare? With all ſpeed, and yet with wiſedome and vnderſtanding, ſet vp Diſcipline &amp; reformation that is amiſſe after Gods booke,<note place="margin">Pſal. 122.3. &amp; 48.5.</note> and you ſhal ſee their hope wil be turned into feare, they will ſee Ieruſalem ſo to be built, as a Cittie at vnitie in it ſelfe, that when they behold it, they will marueill and be aſtonied, and ſuddenly driuen backe. Thus was it with the people of God after their capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie: they neuer had quietnes till Nehemias that worthie Prince aroſe, who though hee were neuer ſo much put in fear, that he was driuen to cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to work with one hand, &amp; hold the weapon with the other,<note place="margin">Nehem. 6.16.</note> yet he neuer ceaſed til he had finiſhed the wal, &amp; made all things in his order about Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, when al the enemies did hear, euen all the heathen that were round about, they were afraid, and their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage failed them, for they knewe that this worke was wrought by God, and ſhall wee, who by her gracious and godly gouernment, are brought out of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Babilon, into the fellowſhip of the Citizens and ſaints of God, doubt more of his bleſſing, if we ſhould
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:728:36"/>ſtriue to garniſhe gods Citie with this goodlye wall of Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline?<note place="margin">maintaineth peace.</note> ſhould not all Papiſtes be forced to ſay, that the Lord hath done this? eſpecially now, when he hath ſo wonderfully driuen backe our enemies. Iehoſophat after that hee had eſcaped in the battaile where Ahab was ſlaine, and had bene admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by Iehu the ſonne of Hananie the Seer, for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king part with the wicked, gaue himſelfe to reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not onely in Iuda, but euen from Beer ſheba to mount Ephraim, hee brought the people againe to the Lord God of their fathers. What folowed? could there any preuaile againſt him? No no: It is written, that the feare of God was vpon all the kingdomes of the earth, when they had hard that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord had fought againſt the enemies of Iſraell,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 19. &amp; cap. 6, 20.29.30.</note> ſo the kingdome of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoſhaphat was quiet, and his God gaue him reſt on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſide. Shall wee thinke that the Lordes hand is ſhortned, if we be as zealous as he?<note place="margin">Exod. 10.26.</note> Moſes would not leaue a hoofe behind him in Egypt: did he ſpeed any whit the worſe in the end? and ſhall we thinke that if ſome Achitophel ſhoulde fortifie ſome wicked Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom, to reſiſt his liege Ladye and peaceable mother; that God woulde not ſtir vp a thouſand Huſhais to ouerthrowe all his counſailes?</p>
            <p>Let vs remember wherein our peace conſiſteth, and the ſtrength thereof: is it not in ſeruing of God, and walking in his commandements, and putting our truſt in his mercy? Then muſt wee take heede of all thoſe Baalamites, who vnder pretence of preuenting rebellion, giue craftie counſail for the diuell: to make vs careleſſe, in our dutie towards God, that when wee refuſe to goe forward, wee might fall backward: and then God proclaime warre againſt vs and ſay, if they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:728:37"/>will not obey,<note place="margin">The Church Gouernment of Chriſt</note> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 12.17. Eſay 57.21. 2. Kin. 12.27.</note> then will I vtterly deſtroy and plucke vp that nation. And againe, there is no peace to the wicked ſaith my God. So was it with Ieroboam, who to eſtabliſhe his kingdome ouer the ten tribes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his poſteritie: he altered the precepts of God and made two Calues, the one in Dan, and the other in Bethell, leaſt the people going vp to worſhip at Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem after Gods lawe, ſhould rebell and fall away from him: but this turned to bee ſuch a ſinne, that it rooted out his houſe, &amp; many other houſes after him, and in the end, the whole ten tribes, whereof hee was king, were ſpued out of that land, ſoe dangerous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing it is to chuſe that pollicie, which is againſt gods lawe and commaundement.</p>
            <p>Nowe in peace as one ſaith,<note place="margin">Chriſts Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline is for the vvealth and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the realme.</note> ſmall things are made great, riches &amp; honour are multiplied. Let vs ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe diſorders doe not maintaine the contrary, I cannot ſay but God hath bleſſed vs in our peace with both, and yet I muſt ſay, that the ſtate of our churches and church gouernement is rather a hinderer. Firſt there lacketh that orderly ſeeing to the poore which were expedient, and men for the moſt part are left to them ſelues, ſo that by idlenes and libertie, great pouettie are among vs, which fal into many noiſome thinges, which might very well be amended by Chriſtes diſcipline. Secondlye there are among vs, ſuffered &amp; nouriſhed by order in Cathedral churches a cloiſter of idle men, who liuing vpon the goods of the Church and Common wealth, do litle or no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice for the ſame. It is a heauy burthen in a common wealth to ſuffer men to liue in pleaſure and eaſe like oxen in a ſtall, to doe almoſt no labour. For moſt of theſe (I wil not ſay all) doe litle or nothing, as by the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:728:37"/>nature of this order they are occaſioned: Is not this to be amended? they wil ſay they are rewardes of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but it is ſcarce good pollicy (as I take it) that when men haue learning, they ſhoulde be maintained to idlenes, and put their learning to no vſe. But they do preach, that is to ſaye, ſome of them ſometimes doe preach, and ſome do hier others to preach for them. But to looke neerely to the thing, one man may do as much as all the orders of the houſe (in the place of the houſe) do require. Then if one of neceſſitie ſhould be there, all the reſt of the liuings might well bee ſpared for the helping of churches which haue ſmal liuings, and to further the encreaſe of learning.</p>
            <p>But as touching honor, it may be that they would ſay, that wee ſhould looſe one eſtate, and ſo the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth decaied in wealth and honour. The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a Common-wealth ſtandeth, not in an eſtate which is of an other nature, but in the honourable and wiſe cariage of true Common-wealth men, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, Iudges, Iuſtices and Captaines. Now when their liuing ſhould bee imployed to better vſes, it would bee a greater honour, and riches of more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable encreaſe. This would (ſay they) turne to the domage of the common treaſure, which by firſt fruits in the remooue of L.Bb. and Cathedrall Prelates, is ſomewhat augmented. Not a whit: for if it were ſo that the money ſhould be caried out of the land, as in times paſt it hath bin to that powling Citie of Rome, then it were ſomething that were ſaid, but ſeeing it is to bee beſtowed in the land, it can be no loſſe. For in the conuaiance, that benefite might be reſerued: yet I pray you, how did out treaſure hold out, when that a great deale more was wanting, which hath come in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:728:38"/>within theſe 80. yeares. If our forefathers in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, thought nothing to much for the Churches ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement, neither almoſt had any ende in giuing their lands and goods that way, ſhall wee thinke that God cannot another way bleſſe vs as much, if we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from alitle, for the competent and decent erecting of his miniſtery? but God be thanked, the Common-wealth (as I hope) may the rather be encreaſed: for if things be wiſely handled, the Miniſtery may bee well and decently maintained, and yet there wil ariſe ſuch a portion of good lands, to be beſtowed at her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties pleaſure, as may make a large recompence by a yearely certaintie, and this will be a great deale more honor to our Common-wealth, to haue Gods houſe well and rightly built, and his ſeruants comely enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, then for the making of one L.B. vnneceſſarily, there ſhould be a hundreth Bb. beſide to the realme,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.1.</note> as poore almoſt as beggers. It would be more honor &amp; wealth to the realm, then to maintain a ſort of idle, red or blew coats, to haue in euery pariſh, an honeſt, &amp; learned B. who in a competent liuing would feed the poore, and by giuing and lending, keepe many a good Subject in heart, that he might be able to ſerue his Prince in time of need.</p>
            <p>In time of peace,<note place="margin">Chriſtes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline cutteth of contention.</note> a great waſter of proſperity is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and ſtrife, and many houſes lie waſt by ſuch inordinate iarring and ſuites of lawe: here to let paſſe howe many ſuits are bred and fed by theſe diſorders, as about aduowſons, priuiledges and preſentments. This one thing wil ſhew the excellency of diſcipline, for the wealth of the Realme and quiet of ſubiectes, that the Church is to cenſure ſuch a party, who is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly troubleſome and contentious, and without
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:728:38"/>reaſonable cauſe, and vpon a meere will and ſtomack doth vex and moleſt his brother, &amp; trouble the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. And the daily ſhowring dew of the preaching of peace, will bring foorth many counſellours of peace, and many, when they ſee that ſuch a thing is vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and to bee anſwered before the Church, will bee well aduiſed what ſuits they take in hand. Thus when the authoritie of the Churche and good preaching, cutteth aſunder the cords of diſcord, men muſt needs increaſe in wealth, and ſo at all times ſhall bee able to beare any burthen that the Common-wealth ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and this will bee a great deale better, then if the treaſure lay vnprofitably and without vſe in Coffers, and to the honor of the Realme farre more excellent, when men ſhall be in all places, found able to relieue themſelues and other.</p>
            <p>Now as concerning warres,<note place="margin">The 5. ſpeciall reaſon.</note> wee may learne of the children of this world, that it is the beſt pollicy to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce the Lords holy Diſcipline, and that as well in the preparation for warre, as in the time of war it ſelfe. This doth altogether further our eſtate. The Bb. of Rome haue Seminaries erected, for the training vp of yong men in their abhominable errors, out of which, as out of the dragons mouth, there go theſe vncleane frogs the Ieſuits and Seminary Prieſts, who go about as it were, by night cloſely and ſecretly croking, at the conſciences of her Maieſties ſubjectes, to bring them from their dutifull obedience and ſubjection. Now in vvarre it is an ordinarye pollicye to haue a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, becauſe the enemie moſt commonly vſeth to vndermine vvhere he cannot vvel come nere in fight. So if vve had Diſcipline, and euery Pariſh his learned Paſtor, theſe creeping crokers would be ſo narrowlie
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:728:39"/>looked vnto,<note place="margin">Diſcipline after Gods word</note> 
               <note place="margin">Chriſtes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin foreſt aleth all ſedition and rebellion.</note> that they could not haue any hole to hide their heads: and the people, would be ſo wel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the knowledge of God in Chriſt Ieſus, and of their duty to their true Soueraigne, that al the frogs in thoſe mooriſh Seminaries, ſhould not be able once to moue them, and by this meanes, ſo prepared for war, if neede be, that whereas nowe there go a great many only with their bodies, and ſome only of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall loue to their Countrey, then would they goe with a reſolute iudgement, and of conſcience to God, they would willingly do any ſeruice, and that, which in this caſe is not ſmall, they would not ſo eaſily bee drawen after any great man, or meane man, to ſedition and rebellion. For how ignoraunt men, are like chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren carried with euery winde, all ſtate men do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Therefore, ſeeing as is already prooued, and al men by too too lamentable experience may knowe, that the nature of our Church gouernement, as it is now vnperfect, doth very ſlowly bring forth, true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute chriſtian men of knowledge: we may eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that it is dangerous for the ſtate to ſuffer it in the Common-wealth, and to let the church bee ouer run with ſuch careleſſe and blind guides.</p>
            <p>Beſides this,<note place="margin">Quietnes in charges for war commeth by Chriſtes holy diſcipline, and wiling ſoldiers.</note> when men haue knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, what is fit for Gods glory, and their duty at ſuch a time: they will not murmure and grudge at euery trifling charge, which commeth to paſſe, for the ſupplie of the warres, but willingly and cherefully, do any thing that may become good Subiectes, in caſes of neceſſity: But what I ſee both in this, and in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for lacke of good teachers, maketh my heart to bleede, and my pen cannot vtter. Wherof thinke you, was it that Abraham ha in his houſe, 318. men, ſo
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:728:39"/>ready at an howers warning,<note place="margin">is good againſt warre.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 14.14. &amp; 18.19.</note> to go with him to purſue them which had taken Lot, but by the good inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; Diſcipline of his houſe, which he is commended for to haue, according to Gods waies? What made the Reubenites, the Gaddites, and the halfe tribe of Manaſſes, ſo willingly to leaue their wiues and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, on the hither ſide of Iorden, and to go before their brethren againſt Canaan,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 1.12.</note> &amp; to bind themſelues on paine of death, euery man to bee obedient to Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua, and to go whither ſo euer hee would ſend them? Was it not becauſe they knew the Lord, and that Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua was appointed by him,<note place="margin">The keeping of Gods orders good for war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like prouiſion. 1. King. 10.26.</note> to bee their gouernour? was there euer king prouided more royally of al ſtore of good things, for peace and for war, then Solomon? Was there any at any time, that did more aduaunce Gods ordinances, then he did in the time, hee got all this aboundance? Who went forward more in al pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and in all plenty and prouiſion for warre, then Vziah, ſo long as he ſought the Lord God, in the dais of Zechariah that vnderſtood the viſion of God? but when his heart was lifted vp, &amp; he preſumed to break the order that God had appointed in his Church, hee became a pittifull leaper, and ſo for his tranſgreſſion, loſt his great honour, which he had of the Lord.<note place="margin">2. Chron. 26.</note> See then, that it is good pollicy, for prouiſion of good and faithfull ſouldiers, and all manner of ſtore of muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for honorable ſeruice in war, to folow gods word, and his ordinances in the gouerning of our churches.</p>
            <p>In vvar it ſelfe, there is nothing more needfull,<note place="margin">Chriſtes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline beſt to make ſoldiers obedient.</note> then faithfull obedience, vvhich vvhere can it be more tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found, either in Captain, or common ſouldier, then vvhere the conſcience is catechiſed in the vvaies of the Lorde: vvhich if it bee vvrought by this, in the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:728:40"/>things of preparation, it will be alſo as firme in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time of vvarre it ſelfe: I vvill not ſay, but ſome thing is, and may be done, as the ſtate of the Church novve ſtandeth, for God be thanked, there bee diuers good Preachers: but the queſtion is, of the beſt and ſureſt pollicie: If now then by a fewe, much good is done, what vvould it be, if euery congregation were rightly informed, and truly reformed? a thouſand to one.</p>
            <p>In warre vnto obedience,<note place="margin">Cotage &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, by Chriſtes diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</note> there is to be linked cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and patience, courage to beare the aſſault of the enemy, his force and terror of warlike weapons, and patience to endure all diſtreſſes, pennury and ſcarcity. Now if men be not wel reſolued by good knowledge of their dutie, they will flie, for feare of the one, &amp; fall to mutinies, for griefe in the other. Therefore if there be in euery congregation, a worthy teacher, hee will be able ſo to prepare theit hearts, that they ſhall ſtand immooueable, with liuelines of ſpirit, to goe through the one, and with modeſt quietnes to go vnder the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: which thing, is not poſſible to bee, where the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Church, ſuffereth or foſtereth ſo many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and rawe ſchollers, which haue more neede to bee taught, then to teach others.</p>
            <p>Againe, the preſence of an honeſt, wiſe, and graue Miniſter (the Captaines can tel) doth more then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny freſh water ſouldiers do think, eſpecially in extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, for he ſhall ſweetly comfort them in grief, migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily imbolden them in feare, meekly ſtay them in rage, and prudently preuent many euils. Hereof was it, that Ioab, that valliant warriour, when hee was beſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and behinde, by the Aramites and Amonites, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing deuided his armie,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.Sam. 10.9.</note> and ſet his battaile in araye, could and did vſe theſe words of encouragement: be
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:728:40"/>ſtrong, and let vs be valiant for our people, and for the cities of our God: and let the Lord doe that which is good in his eies. Hereof was it, that when Saneherib, king of A ſhur, beſiedged Ieruſalem with a mightye hoaſt, and ſent his ſeruantes to raile vpon God, and to make weake the hands of the people:<note place="margin">2. Cron. 32. Eſay. 36.</note> There was great ſilence by the ſeruantes of Hezekiah that godly king, and no man ſtirred, for he had cauſed them to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the wayes of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Laſt of al,<note place="margin">Ordering the Church aright bringeth ſtrength and victory in war.</note> that you might know how good a pollicy it is, for ſtrength &amp; victory in war, to haue the church ordered aright, with the proper offices, and proper works, namely what corage it may worke, and what good ſucceſſe it may bring in the end, conſider well the battel which Abijath the ſonne of Rehoboam had with Ieroboam the ſonne of Nebat. The firſt being king of Iuda bringeth into the field, 400000. able figh ting men, the other being king of Iſrael had 800000. valiant men of war. Abijath ſetting his men in aray,<note place="margin">2. Cron. 13.</note> calleth vnto Iſrael, and admoniſheth them to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that they had forſaken their God, and therefore ſhould not proſper: amongeſt other thinges he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to this preſent point: and ſayth: Haue you not driuen away the Prieſts of the Lord, the ſonnes of Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron and the Leuites, and haue made you prieſtes like the people of other countries, &amp;c. And againe, but we belong to the Lord our God, and haue not forſaken him, and the prieſts the ſonnes of Aaron miniſter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, and the Leuits in their offices, &amp;c. and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Behold, this God is with vs as a Captaine, and his prieſts with the ſounding trumpets to cry alarum againſt you. O yee children of Iſrael, fight not againſt the lord God of your fathers, for you ſhal not proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:728:41"/>Loe here what courage, and confidence, the true order of Gods miniſterie may breede and bring forth. in the day of a dangerous battel, let vs heare the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. Ieroboam cauſed an ambuſh to compaſſe Iuda behinde, ſo that the battel was behinde &amp; before: but the men of Iuda cryed vnto the Lord, the prieſts blew the trumpets, and the people gaue a ſhoute: and the men of Iſrael fled before them, and were ſlaine with an exceeding greatſlaughter, ſo that there fel downe wounded of Ifrael, 500000. of choſen men, and Iſrael was brought vnder, and Iuda preuailed, becauſe they ſtayed vpon the lord God of their fathers. Oh happy ſucceſſe: oh wonderful victory, bleſſed is that people who can followe this example, to reforme themſelues after Gods lawe, and to order the churches with theſe holy adminiſtrations, &amp; ſanctified works which God hath appointed, &amp; to leaue the proude, antichriſtian, prophane, vncleane, lame, blinde offices and officers, of countries eſtranged from God, and the vnholy &amp; defiled rites and ceremonies of the vnrighteous Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, from whence we are returned vnto the city of the liuing God.</p>
            <p>Let vs nowe looke vnto the church,<note place="margin">The fixt ſpecial reaſon of the Church.</note> and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther al be well and ſafe: namely whether it were not better &amp; ſafer to haue reformation after Gods word: the Church is called Gods houſe,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.15. 1. Cor. 12.28. Cap. 4.1. Heb 5 4. Mat. 25.14. 1. Cor 12.6. 1. Pet 4.10. 1. Cor. 11.23. Act. 20.27.</note> the miniſters are Gods ſtewards, ſet in by him, and noe man is to take this honor except he be called, and thoſe he putteth in office haue talents, theſe worke the workes of God, both to ſpeake the oracles of God, and to miniſter of the abilitie which God miniſtreth, deliuering that which they receue of the Lord, &amp; teaching the whole counſell of God that the church may obſerue whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:728:41"/>Chriſt hath commaunded,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.20. 1. Tim. 6.14.</note> &amp; that without ſpott and vnrebukeable vntil the appearing of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. When therefore it is already declared, and al men may ſee that many offices, workes, &amp; rites, are added to that of Chriſtes out of the houſe of Anti-Chriſt, &amp; that many of theſe, want that which Chriſt hath appointed, and that the houſe of God is daubed with vntempered morter of mans deuiſe, with hey &amp; ſtubble not agreeing with the foundation, and that the church is his trueſpouſe, and with vs is maimed,<note place="margin">Chriſt many waies calleth vs to reforme out churches after his word.</note> in many members, and her nakednes &amp; woundes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, with the filthy and ſtinking clouts and patches borowed of that damnable whore of Rome, Chriſtes mortall enemie. I cannot tell howe it can be ſafe for our churches if they be not reformed, for if we be the temple of God, and he dwelleth amonge vs,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.26.</note> we are to knowe, that he calleth vs to come out of Babilon, and to ſeperate our ſelues, &amp; to touch noe vncleane thing that he may receiue vs: &amp; if we ſuffer our lord Chriſt to ſtand and knocke at our doores,<note place="margin">Cantie. 5.2.</note> as it is ſayd in the Canticles, til his head be ful of dewe, and his lockes with the droppes of the night: &amp; we as halfe a ſleepe and halfe a wake, are loath to goe out of our warme beddes, to put one our clothes, and to foule our feet: it may come to paſſe, that when we would open vnto him, he wil be gone, and when we ſhal ſeeke him, we ſhal not find him, and call for him, &amp; he not anſwere: and that counterfeit watchmen, of the wicked Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, ſhall finde vs, and beat vs, as in times paſt, and take awaye the vaile of Chriſt from vs: then will wee thinke, that it had bene better to haue beene zealous, and opened vnto him, that he might haue come in,<note place="margin">Reue. 3.20.</note> &amp; ſupped with vs, and we with him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:728:42"/>
To leaue out all other thinges,<note place="margin">Chriſts orders, taught in the goſpel,</note>
               <note place="margin">Chriſts church gouernment, beſt for vnitie and honour of the miniſtery.</note> eſpecially, becauſe they are partly contained in the former reaſons: there are two things, that men marueilouſly ſtand vpon, for the vpholding of this Antichriſtian lordlines, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation of Church gouernment: the dignitie of the Miniſtery, and the vnity of the Church: two thinges of very great waight, whereof the one is ſo great, that euery miniſter ought to looke very carefully to it, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying to ſhew himſelfe approoued, a workeman that needeth not to bee aſhamed,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.15. Titus 2.15.</note> deuiding the worde of truth aright: ſpeaking, exhorting, and rebuking withal authority: the other is ſuch, that if it be not looked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, the contrary thereof, is the ruine and downfall of the Church,<note place="margin">Oala. 5.15.</note> as it is written: if you bite and deuoure one another, take heed leaſt you be conſumed, one of another. Now ſay they, if there were not L.Bb. the pore miniſters would be borne downe, and made no account of, but they are a countenaunce and defence vnto them, and whereas, euery one would be maiſter, and doe as they liſt, by them, men are kept in awe, and things are made quiet: therefore you know not what you do, when you go about to pull them down. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a goodly ſhew at the firſt ſight, but not ſuch as will abide the breath of God. Is not Chriſt ſufficient, that hath promiſed to be with his ſeruants vnto the worlds end, to countenance and defend his miniſtery, as wel as he did three hundreth yeares together, when al the power of earthly authoritie was againſt it, and ſhall he need now a deuiſe which hee long ſince forbad: ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it ſhall not beſo with you, but he that will be gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, let him be your ſeruant,<note place="margin">Luke 22.25.</note> eſpecially, when hee hath reared vp the chriſtian magiſtrate, to bee a nurſe-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his church, and to defend all the miniſters for
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:728:42"/>well doing,<note place="margin">be beſt for the churches ſafty.</note> as ſhe doth all other ſubiectes in their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: and is not Chriſt by his owne order, as wel able to keepe his church in vnity, as by that which hee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred: and may not alſo the ciuill ſword (if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire) helpe to bridle the inſolent and vnruly?</p>
            <p>But in very deed, theſe men are greatly deceiued, who thinke, that either vnity, or good miniſters, are furthered by their lordſhips: for as their callinges are not of God, ſo they countenance ſuch as are like them ſelues, corrupt offices and workes, Cathedrall chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, non-reſidence, pluralities, dumb Idoll miniſters, &amp;c. Theſe, if they ſubſcribe, and ſhewe them ſelues conformable, though they ſlay neuer fo many ſoules, ſhall be borne out and countenaunced to the vtmoſt. I would we had not too lamentable experience: what a countenance is this? that though a man liue neuerſo honeſtly-preach Chriſt neuer ſo ſoundly, wiſely, and profitably, yet if he anſwere not their expectation, in that baſtardly gouernement, and canonicall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he ſhall be as much regarded, as though he were the vileſt man aliue: and I would it were not true, that very wicked men are maintained, while good men are put out, and can any thing bee more to the contempt of the Miniſtery &amp; rent of the church, and making of ſeiſme, then when men are quiet, and follow their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, with great care of the peace of the church, they ſhould be called forth to ſubſcribe, to humain conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, as vnto the boke of God: &amp; without due time of examination, conſideration, &amp; reſolution, to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpended or depriued, and toſſed from court to court, what can make the goſpel more hated, then to ſee bad fellows, &amp; dumb Idols to be ſet free, with credite and commendacion, &amp; they that haue woon many to the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:728:43"/>feare of God,<note place="margin">Engliſh books, ſeene &amp; allowed,</note> &amp; duty to her Maieſty, by diligent prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: euen againſt the law of God and man, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled with troubles, torne and turmoiled with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers moleſtations.</p>
            <p>And is this the fruit of vnity, that is pretended? to beginne the quarrell with the quiet, and to purſue it with all violence, to make them, who in towne and country were very greatly at vnity, tooke ſweet coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell togither, for the profiting of the church, to be now ſundred as ſtrangers? O Lord deliuer my ſoule from ſuch honour and vnitie, and deliuer thy pore ſeruants from ſuch bondage and contempt, and thy Churches from ſuch reptoches and diſturbance.</p>
            <p>But if theſe diſorders were remooued, and Chriſts Diſcipline planted, where were all theſe miſchiefes? they would be throwen into the bottome of the Sea: then would be the glory and beauty of the miniſtery, in the true worke of euery calling, and the power of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Chriſts Diſcip. taketh away the cauſeof conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</note> which accompanieth the ſame: then would be the vnity of the Church, when their cauſes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention ſhould be taken away, and the houſe of God, ioyned and built with the right ſtuffe &amp; gold of God, and Gods grace in the middeſt of it. Then ſhould the Papiſt quaile, to ſee the glory of Chriſtes kingdome: then ſhould the Annabaptiſt waile, that he hath abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Gods people: Then ſhould the Atheiſt be forced to ſtand amazed, at the woonderfull brightnes of the chaſt and holy ſpouſe of God, looking forth, as the morning,<note place="margin">Cantic. 6.9.</note> faire as the moone, pure as the ſunne, terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as an army with banners: For this I hope, all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines will grant me,<note place="margin">All diſorder &amp; ſciſme, by brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Chriſts orders.</note> that there neuer was, or can be in the church, by the members thereof, any diſhonour, ſciſme, diſorder, or diſquietnes, but by the breach of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:728:43"/>the law, and order of Chriſt: whereof,<note place="margin">teach Chriſts diſcip. for our ſaſty</note> in all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of Gods ſpirite, you ſhall finde theſe, and ſuch like phraſes. Diuiſions and diſcenſions,<note place="margin">Rom. 16.7. 1. Cor. 11.18.22. 2. Theſ. 3.14. Gal. 16.16 cap. 1.7.5.8 Math. 15.6.9.</note> contrary to the doctrine ye haue receiued. I haue receiued of the Lorde, that which I alſo deliuered vnto you. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw your ſelues from euery brother, that walketh in ordinatly, and not after the inſtruction which hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of vs. As many as walke acording to this rule, peace ſhalbe vppon them.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.3.</note> It is not the perſwaſion of him that calleth you,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.14.20</note> you haue made the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God of no authority by your traditions: &amp; ſuch like: therefore I may boldely holde,<note place="margin">Iude. 3.4.</note> that Chriſts Church gouernement is beſt for the Church euerie way, and namely for the honour and vnitie thereof.</p>
            <p>And here I moſt humbly beſeech the reuerend fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by the mercies of God our father,<note place="margin">An humble ſpeech to the Bb.</note> by the conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which is in Chriſt leſus our Sauiour, &amp; by the fellowſhip of the ſpirit, by whom we be renewed, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting apart, al affection to themſelues, and faction with others, in a ſimple and ſingle eie, to conſider theſe few things. Firſt, that ſeeing by themſelues, in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſermons, and writings, and other bookes, ſet forth with authority and priuilege: The ſeekers of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may learne,<note place="margin">Sermons of Thomas, B. of Lincoine pag. 5</note> that the gouernement and direction by Gods worde, preuaileth more, than any deuiſe of man: and that there are infinite examples, of vnarmed men, who obeying gods commandements, haue ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the moſt puiſſant armies of the infidels,<note place="margin">Antimartinus page 26.</note> and of moſt mightie Emperors, who for mingling ſomtime, and ſometime chaunging the precepts of the Lorde, with their inuentions, haue com vnder moſt vile bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wher the people are not taught, they can not ſerue God, the Prince is not ſo dutifully obeied,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:728:44"/>the rebellion in the North is proofe of that.<note place="margin">D. Some in his treatiſe of deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding certaine queſtions. pa. 8 D. Bilſon in his defence of the Queenes ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy part 2. pag. 233.</note> And that this authority which you haue, was not ordained by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of Chriſt, for his Apoſtles, but by ſufferance of other Bb. and that onely with this prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue, that in all doubtes of doctrine or diſcipline Archbb. and patriarks might aſſemble the reſt of their brethren, or conſult them with letters, &amp; ſee that ob. ſerued which the moſt part of them determined.<note place="margin">Luther on 1. Pet. 5. ver. 2.</note> So that the Biſhops are greater, then Miniſters or Elders, rather by cuſtome, then by any truth of the Lords ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, and ought to gouerne the church in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,<note place="margin">M. Nowelin his Catechiſme fol. 40 B.</note> and that there is deſcribed out of Gods worde, a certaine order of gouernance and forme of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical diſcipline, which ought to be obſerued in euery Church, if it be well ordered: which by deſire of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punitie, and libertie to ſin, is long ſince decayed. And ſeeing we haue moſt plainely and perfectlie teaching, the whole diſciplin out of the word of god, &amp; ancient writers, and Cannons of the Church, tranſlated into the Engliſh tongue. Peter Martirs Common-places, Caluins-Inſtitutions, Bullingers Decads, Bezaes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, the Apoligie of the Proteſtants of Fraunce, and diuers others: Whereof, ſome I haue ſeene lying openly to be read in ſome of your gret chambers, ſome are commanded to bee ſtudied, by the vnlearned mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery,<note place="margin">Keeping out of Chriſts Diſcr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, litle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the Bb.</note> and all printed with publike allowance. Here I ſay, you are to conſider, whether it be equal and iuſt, for you to do contrary to your doctrine: to puniſh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for ſeeking humbly, that reformation in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, which by your meanes, they haue learned to be according to Gods worde. or what comfort you can haue in your conſciences, (if God ſhould but a little call you to account) to ſtand ſo ſtiffe for that, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:728:44"/>but confeſſe to bee of mans cuſtome, againſt that which was of Chriſts inſtitution. And laſtly, whether you can be ſayd to haue a care of the ſafety of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and the good floriſhing eſtate of this land, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially now, when God calleth vs vnto repentance and reformation by many troubles, when you do ſo aeger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fight for that, which made the mightie Emperors, vile ſlaues, and that againſt ſuch a thing, as made the naked men great conquerours.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing that nowe thirtie yeares, taking vpon you, the gouerning of all the Churches in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, you haue put out more godly,<note place="margin">Litle good in 30. yeares by all our Bb. gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> learned, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Miniſters, for your owne traditions: then you haue remooued, of other vnfit and vngodly, for brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gods commaundements: and that S. Paule ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing but a while preached at Creta, an Iſland of an hundreth Cities, left Titus there after his departure, to ſet all things in order, and namely, a learned miniſtery in euery Citie,<note place="margin">Titus 2.5. cap. 3.12.</note> (and that without helpe of the ciuill Magiſtrate) appointing him to ſtaye but till winter, and then to come to him to Nicapolis. Conſider I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, that in ſo many winters and ſummers, in this little Iſland, you haue done ſo little good, and cry out ſtill, it is impoſſible to haue a learned Miniſterie, when you haue the moſt renowned Prince in the world for religion, to backe you with ciuill power and countenance. As it is to her immortall fame, to giue you this libertie &amp; authority, thinking it not to much to aduanceyou to great dignity and honour: ſo, wey with your ſelues, what may bee thought of you, that haue ſo meanely diſcharged the great truſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto you.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, where you ſaye, that the godly ſeekers of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:728:45"/>reformation,<note place="margin">The Bb. diſturbers</note> 
               <note place="margin">The godly ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contend not for trifies.</note> contend about trifles, (which is not ſo) and that they ought not for ſmall matters, to diſturbe the peace of the Church, and prouoke her Maieſtie. Conſider I pray you: whether that, when you doe ſo earneſtly ſtand to maintaine them, and are not as ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt againſt the greater offences, ſuffering thouſands of ſoules to periſh, by ignorant miniſters and non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents, you tithe not mint, and leaue out the waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie matters of the law, and whether you ought not for the peace and good of the Church, to yeeld to your brethren,<note place="margin">Gen. 13.8.9.</note> in that you count ſmal matters (as Abraham did to Lot) eſpecially, ſeing youcannot deny, but that they ſeek that which God commandeth, &amp; refuſe that which is of mans ordinance, &amp; that, not as new fang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led heads, and ſingular, but with the agreement and conſent of moſt approoued, both olde and new wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and as moſt reformed Churches haue alſo deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and practiſed. Conſider I beſeech you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whether the word of God went from you,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.36.</note> or came onely vnto you, and that when in ſo many years, you haue found theſe thinges to be inconuenient,<note place="margin">The Bb. make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſlaues to their owne orders.</note> it vvere not your duty, to do as the Apoſtle ſaith, that in lawful things, which were not profitable, he would not bee brought in ſubiection vnto any thing,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.12.</note> which while you neglect: Conſider I pray you, whether it bee not you, that diſturbe the peace of the Church, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the good and peaceable minde of our gracious Soueraigne, againſt your brethen, and that you haue not neede to take heede, leaſt the maiſter of the houſe come ſuddenly vpon you, and find you beating your fellows,<note place="margin">Math. 24.49.</note> and ſeperate you, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, wheras you miſtruſt ſome Machiauilian plot, by deepe ſleights, to maintaine this contention, for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:728:45"/>the bringing forth of diuers miſchiefs,<note place="margin">Admonition to the people of Eug by T.C. page. 155. Antimartin. page 24.25.</note> noyſome to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and godlines, and hurtfull to your ſelues. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I beſeeche you, whether it bee not in you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent it: For if you would leaue diſcountenauncing of your brethren, for that which you call ſmall matters, and ioyne with them in humble ſuite to her Maieſtie,<note place="margin">It is in the Bb. to remedy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchiefs.</note> to take away all the ſtumbling blocks of offence, or at leaſt wiſe, obtaine ſome godly toleration, if you wold not leaue your brethren, nay oppoſe your ſelues, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>profeſſo, againſt them, and haue your eares ſo open to popiſh information, and malicious accuſation, and force them by oth, to be their owne accuſers.<note place="margin">Luke. 6.26.</note> Yf you could ſee what it is, to bee ſo highly commended, by open recuſants, and deſperate Atheiſts, and that the worſer ſort of people, vnder the ſhadowe of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, begin to make an head, and to bee ſtrong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the goſpell, and the ſincere profeſſors thereof: you might eaſily cut in ſunder, and breake to powder, all the pollitike reaches which you feare: For what is it, that the ioyned labours of faithfull brethren might not do? But when you make light of theſe things, wey with your ſelues I pray you, whether you haue not great cauſe to ſuſpect, your own inconſiderat doings, and to feare, if God preuent it not, your dealing with your brethren (as Eliab with Dauid) be not volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtruments of your own ouerthrow,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.28.</note> and of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, while you weaken your ſelues, by cutting of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, your faithfull brethren, by vniuſt ſeperation, and that (which many men bewaile, when they beholde the increaſe of your giftes, and other your dealinges) whither it be not fulfilledin you, which is prophecied againſt them that teach the feare of God by mens pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes, namely, a ſtrange worke and a woonder: The
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:728:46"/>wiſedome of the wiſe ſhal periſh,<note place="margin">Eſay. 29.13.14</note> &amp;c. I pray God giue vs all grace, that we be not wayward conceited, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piniate by contention &amp; vaine glory, prouoking one another, and enuying one another, but that our care may be vnited to tender the yong lambes, for whome Chriſt Ieſus our Lord and Sauiour, did ſhed his moſt precious bloud.</p>
            <p>Seeing then,<note place="margin">The end of the ſpeciall reaſons.</note> that the Diſcipline of Chriſt, doth moſt properly teach euery ſoule to execute and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe good lawes, both for the conſtant doctrine, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually taught, &amp; alſo for the Elderſhip being at hand, without charge of penaunce, reforming the diſobe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and that the other gouernment miniſtreth leſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, and practiſeth the cenſures a far of, by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon vnfit, with chaunge of penaunce, and that wicked men, loue this, and hate that, and that this kepeth out good men, and that helpeth them in: ſeing, by the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Chriſt, the Queenes ſafty is beſt prouided for, being a thing of obedience vnto proſperity: and by it, al the helpes of Antichriſt be remooued, and the other orders, haue alwais hurt the lawfull authority of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to be chiefe B. in one countrey, is all one, as to be chief Biſhop in one Empire, and theſe haue hurt kings, as well as our Popes the Emperour: and that by the common law and theſe offices, there is a hope left, for the deadlieſt enemy to her Maieſty to enter in, &amp; that papiſts (who in conſcience can neuer be true, nor by rewards bee made faithfull) are fit for ſuch offices, to couer themſelues and others, that for lacke of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and by licenſes, the breed of Papiſts is not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, neither can the doubtfull be euery where reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and that Chriſts lawes do take away all theſe, and make faithfull and obedient ſubiects, keeping out the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:728:46"/>recuſants, and bewraying the Ieſuits, and that the ill orders do hardly intreat the doers of ſuch good works and that Chriſts Diſcipline, doth giue all kings their iuſt titles, prerogatiues, and dignities ouer all perſons in their dominions, and that in all cauſes, keeping out al ignorant, wicked, and flattering men, making ſtrong y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> league with chriſtian Princes, to her immortal fame, and feare to the enemy, ſeeing that by this holy diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of GOD, the Nobility and Comminalty haue their right: are freed from diuers wrongs and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances, receiuing comfort to themſelues, &amp; their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, being terrible to the wicked, &amp; eaſie to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: ſeeing that by Diſcipline, there can be no feare of rebellion, but a ſure confirmation of peace, when all hope ſhall be taken away from the knowne aduerſary of recouering ſtrength in this Lande, beholding the Lords hand to proſper this worke, and that the Lord ſhal not be prouoked againſt vs, for our diſobedience: and that by this, the wealth and honour of the realme are increaſed, and contentions, and brawles, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary pleas preuented and alaied: &amp; that idle men, of all ſorts, might be ſet in order, and poore men great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comforted. Seeing that this maketh beſt for war, as in the preparation to preuent all ſeducers of the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful ſubiect, and by inſtruction, to make men reſolute, in the right, ſo that they wil not be drawen after great or ſmall, nor murmure at any paines, or charges reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, but be alwaies willing, ready, and cheerefull to ſerue her Maieſty: and that GOD hath giuen them great ſtore of munition, and faithfull ſouldiers, who followed his ordinaunce, and puniſhed the contrary, and that in the war it ſelfe, it maketh courage to fight, and patience to beare extremities, vnited to iuſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:728:47"/>of the Magiſtrate,<note place="margin">Church-gouerne. after gods word</note> making Princes in time of danger bold and confident, and in the end victorious.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſeeing that Chriſt hath ordained all manner of offices and workes of his Church, for the right or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and eſtabliſhing thereof: and therefore it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, and an vngodly thing, prouoking Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to defile it with the things of Antichriſt, and that Chriſt doth call vs to repentaunce, and that hee hath promiſed ſufficiently to defend his Church in honour and vnity, by his owne order and meanes by him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and hath added for that purpoſe, the ciuill Magiſtrate, and that by theſe diſorders, all diſhonor to the good Miniſterie, and diſturbaunce to the Church hath bene broched, and neuer any diſhonor, confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or diſquietnes, did or can come to the Church, by the members thereof, but by violating the ſacred lawe of Chriſt. I beſeech, and humbly mooue your honors to conſider, whether it be not the beſt and ſureſt polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, for our eſtate in England, to reforme all diſorders after the worde of God, and to ſet vp that Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment which Chriſt hath ordeined, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles practiſed and no other.</p>
            <p>Nowe,<note place="margin">The laſt proofe taken from the iudgement of Chriſt.</note> if in ciuill pollicie, all that I ſayd were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, (which I am verily perſwaded is not ſo) yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtians, there is further matter, and more reaſon for vpholding of that diſcipline which God ordained For we by profeſſion (if wee bee not counterfeit) by beliefe alſo of the heart,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.9. 1. Tim. 4.8.</note> looke not onely to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of this life,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> by Chriſt our Lord and ſauiour, but alſo of the life to come, and do know that we ſhall all appeare before the ſeat of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Act. 10.42.</note> who ſhall come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to take account of his ſeruants, &amp; of euery man,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.6.</note> and render vnto euery one according to the workes
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:728:47"/>which he hath done in his body, either good or bad,<note place="margin">is beſt againſt the great day.</note> and that theſe are to bee iudged by the lawe of God,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.12.</note>&amp; not of man: Therefore, when we know theſe things are the commaundements of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.37. Rom. 16.26. 1. Tim. 1.9.10 11. Gal. 5.21.</note> and that ſuch as continue obſtinate in the breach thereof, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, ſhall not inherite the kingdome of heauen: it were not good pollicy for vs to obtain a litle peace, wealth, honour, and eaſe in this world,<note place="margin">Luke. 16.25. Rom. 2.9. 1 Cor. 9.25.27.</note> to purchaſe al miſerie, diſquietnes, anguiſhe, ſhame and torment in the world to com, for loue of our bodies, to leeſe both body and ſoule: for an earthly crowne, to leeſe a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> for the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note> to leeſe the pleaſures of the righteous God for euer, and to auoyd a light and momentany affliction among men, to leeſe an eternall &amp; exceeding waight of glory:<note place="margin">Reuel. 6.15.16.17.</note> when kings of the earth, great men, rich men, and the chiefe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, the mighty men, and euery bond man, and free man ſhall couet to hide them ſelues in the great and terrible day from the lambe: when hee that hath not on the wedding garment ſhall be ſpeechleſſe,<note place="margin">Math. 22.12. cap. 25.26.28. cap. 24.48. Reuel. 19.20.</note> and the euill ſeruant and ſlothfull, ſhall haue his tallent taken from him, and ſuch as thinke he will deferre his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and begin to ſmite his fellowes, and eat &amp; drink with the drunken, ſhall bee cut off and caſt into vtter darkenes: when the beaſt and the falſe Prophet ſhall be taken &amp; caſt aliue into the lake of fire, burning with brimſtone, and all vncleane thinges whatſoeuer,<note place="margin">cap. 21.10.27.</note> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth abhomination or lies,<note place="margin">cap. 22.18.</note> ſhal be kept out of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heauenly Ieruſalem, and they that adde or take away from Gods booke:<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.7.</note> ſhall haue the plagues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in written, and leeſe their part in the booke of life, when the lord Ieſus ſhal ſhew himſelfe from heauen, with his mighty angels, in flaming fire, rendering ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:728:48"/>vnto them that do not know God, and which obey not the goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall be puniſhed with euerlaſting perdition, from the preſence of the Lord, &amp; the glory of his power, when he ſhal come to be glorified in his ſaints, &amp; to be made marueilous in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleeue:<note place="margin">Luke. 16.29. Math. 17.5.</note> then ſhall it be found the beſt and ſureſt pollicy, to haue heard Moſes &amp; the prophets,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.20.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beloued ſon of god: then ſhal it be known that the temple of the Lord is built vpon the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the apoſtles &amp; prophets,<note place="margin">cap. 4.11.12.13.</note> Ieſus Chriſt being the chief corner ſtone: and that he hath giuen gifts for the gathering together of the ſaints, for the worke of the miniſtery, &amp; for the edification of the body of Chriſt, til we all meet togither, in the vnity of faith, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſoone of God vnto a perfect man, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the meaſure of the age of the fulnes of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Nowe,<note place="margin">The ſecond part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke anſwering the obiection, of prouiſion for the learned mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie.</note> while wee of good and ſingle meaning, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the neceſſitie of reformation, other which neuer peraduenture deſerued any thing of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, ſtand gaping to run away with the ſpoiles, of ſuch goods as may bee well beſtowed, vpon the great need of many churches. I haue thought good there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, partly, becauſe it may appeare, that in this ſtile, I ſhout not againſt any mans perſon, or enuy or deſire his goods: and partly, becauſe it ſeemeth amongeſt many, to be a great obiection: how ſufficient liuings ſhould ariſe,<note place="margin">How liuing may be had for a leathed mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery is a great obiection</note> for the maintenaunce of a learned Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie: and eſpecially, that it is high time to conſider of it, before that by leaſing, chopping, and changing of ſuch things as might ſupply the want, it be made in deed a hard matter, which as yet, may very well and eaſily be done. I haue thought good (I ſay) and apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to this treatiſe, to ſhew a way how, the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:728:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>may haue ſufficient liuing for an able miniſtery, wherin as in the reſt: I only make an humble motion, &amp; as it were, the light opening of a window, put your wiſedomes in minde of this thing, which I take to bee one principall matter, worthy conſideration, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that with farre more deepnes of iudgement, and ſoundnes of counſell, you are able to enlarge, either where it wanteth, or to cut of where it aboundeth.</p>
            <p>Two thinges in this, I hope I ſhall not neede to ſtand vppon, that is, firſt to ſhewe that there are many mean liuings for miniſters, partly by impropriations, and partly by the littlenes or ſituation of the pariſhes,<note place="margin">Many means liuings for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note> for this is in the knowledge of al men very cleare, that there are diuers liuinges, that are not worth aboue 20. markes yearly, ſome twenty pounds, which come no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing neer that competency, that were fit for the man of God: who in this laſt age, not hauing gifts extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, is driuen to ſtudy much, and thereby his char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be increaſed, by buying of books and order of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et &amp; ſome thing for the decenſy of that calling, would be conſidered in the comlines of aparrell and houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, that it bee not contemptible, and laſtly,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2.</note> it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, that he ſhould keepe hoſpitallity, all which, by many degrees cannot come ſo low as twenty marks or twenty pound, as if we looke vpon the proportion of Gods prouiſion vnder the law, which the holy Ghoſt teacheth to be our paterne 1. Cor. 9.8.9.10.<note place="margin">Miniſtesought to haue very good maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Num. 38. &amp; 28</note> it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare: there ſhall wee find, that for the maintenaunce of the Miniſterie, they had not onely the tenthes and conuenient dwelling places, but euen all the firſt fruites, and of all offeringes of diuers ſortes, and they vvere bound to three feaſtes euerye yeare, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides euery newe moone and Sabbaoth) wherein e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:728:49"/>male was to appeare before the Lorde,<note place="margin">How a learned miniſtery may haue</note> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 15. &amp; 16 &amp; 12 Leuit. 23.</note> but hee might not come emptie: yetin al theſe, and many mo charges, they proſpered, though it ſeemed neuer ſo chargeable, ſo long as they willingly ſerued God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his order, and for ſo much as our land, by the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God, may well be accounted among the fertile and rich ſoiles of the world: I hope we are not ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull, as to recompence God, with a vile and baſe entertainement of his ſeruaunts, vnderſtanding very well,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.11.</note> that it is a ſmall matter, that the Miniſter ſhould reape carnall things of them, vpon whome they ſowe ſpirituall things.</p>
            <p>The other thing, which I truſt I ſhall not neede to ſtand vppon is this: that ſeeing there is neede, and that very great, that the miniſtery ſhould be better pro uided for: It were the dutie of the Common wealth, to conuert thoſe thinges (which by their foundation were firſt ment and ordained for the ſeruice of God,<note place="margin">The Church li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings are to be beſtowed one the miniſters.</note> and now haue bene, and are in the opinion of al men beſtowed to that vſe) in the time of reformation, ſhuld be kept for that very vſe, that the reforming of things be not thought rather a bait to feede our bellies, then to proceed of any godly zeale, or loue of religion, for who would not thinke it a plain mockery of God, and a ſcorne of godlines, that men going about to beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Church, ſhould rob and ranſacke the ſame: and pretending to further the ſeruice of God, ſhould giue occaſion to prophaneit? This were the moſt diueliſh pollicy in the world, and the onely ingen almoſt, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow both Prince and people: For God ſaith, if men offer the blinde and the lame vnto a prince,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.7. cap 3.9.</note> hee would not be content, nor accept the perſon, and ſhal we thinke that God can put it vp at our handes, if the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:728:49"/>things of his holines ſhould be lightly regarded,<note place="margin">Sufficient maintenance.</note> &amp; that his embaſſadours ſhould bee ſo ſpitefully ſhauen,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10. 2. Sam. 10.4.</note> and their coates cut off to the middle. No, no: hee will not take it in good part: for in the zeale of his wrathfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, hee pronounceth ſuch men accurſed,<note place="margin">Hag. 1.9.10.</note> with a curſe, becauſe they haue ſpoiled him, and maketh the heauen ouer them to ſtay it ſelfe from dew, &amp; the earth to ſtay her fruit, becauſe his houſe lieth waſt. I hope ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we will hearken vnto Solomon, who ſaith: Honour the Lord with thy riches,<note place="margin">Prouerb. 3.9.</note> and with the firſt fruites of all thine increaſe: ſo ſhall thy barnes be filled with aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and thy preſſes ſhall burſt with newe wine. Be it far from vs in ſo cleare light of the goſpel, we ſhould be flower in this duty, then our forefathers, who did they know not what.</p>
            <p>The matter then I will ſtand vpon, is the thing which may thus be imployed, what it is, and how it is to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: The firſt point what it is, may partly bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by that which is already ſpoken:<note place="margin">VVhat may ſcrue to make ſufficient li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned miniſtery in England.</note> for I meane the Archbb. and L.Bb. liuings, and al the Cathedral chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, houſes and lands, &amp; whatſoeuer profits adioyned excepting the free ſchools, &amp; alms houſes, or ſuch like, which vnto ſome of them belong. The nature of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as may appeare by that which is already decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the good of our land requireth, that theſe dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities or ſpirituall promotions, which are not of Gods planting, ſhould be pulled vp by the rootes, &amp; the men of thoſe places (ſuch as are fit for learning and reuerend behauior) applied and tied to ſome congregation, where they ſhould labor to feed ſoules: then would there be many a faire pallace voyd of a maiſter, and goodly hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, churches, and lands voyd of owners. Here I take it to bee the duty of the common wealth to keepe theſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:728:50"/>liuings ſtill for the maintenance of the Miniſtery, ſeeing there is a very great need of them, and to chaunge one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the order and manner of the applying: that whereas before they ſerued to vpholde a lordly pompe, idlenes and brauerie in ſome fewe: they might nowe by a wiſe and godly diſtribution, be communicated vnto many: for the benefite of many Churches. The lands, houſes, and pallaces may be ſould, and the money beſtowed to the redeeming of impropriations and increaſe of ſmall liuings: and ſurely, this is of all other moſt equall, that where the people do pay their tenthes vnder the name and proprietie of the Churches vſe, they ſhould bee ſo applied indeede. And againe: ſeeing the corruption of our time, hath made impropriations, as fee ſimple landes, they which haue reaſonable recompence for the value of them they poſſeſſe, ſhould by no meanes thinke them ſelues iniured. It is no reaſon that ſeeing the people do already ſtand burdened with ſuch a great charge, that they ſhould bee oppreſſed with a ſecond, eſpecially when there is a meanes to releeue them. And it is againſt all conſcience, that the Miniſterie ſhould be left without iuſtand comely prouiſion &amp; maintenance. But of all other,<note place="margin">Forſlow not the time till the Bb. and Cathedrall Prelates haue waſted all.</note> it were moſt vnvviſe, and vngodly, to foreſlowe the occaſion, eſpecially when the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth was neuer ſo rich, by yearely fruits and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities. And it is yet more horrible wickednes, that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men (although peraduenture ſome of them haue done ſeruice) ſhould preuent the Church, and commit ſo great ſacriledge. For if they deſerue, there is ſufficient beſides to reward them. There is no good Chriſtian, or man, either of valure for fortitude, and wiſedome, or of eſtimation for religion and honeſtye, or of any good name for iuſtice and clemency, can bee of ſo baſe and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:728:50"/>ſeruile a mind, as to grope after the ſpoile and hauocke of the Churche, or to ſuffer himſelfe to bee rewarded with thoſe goodes, which ſhould by all reaſon and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,<note place="margin">A good man will not enrich himſelfe, with that which ſhould ſerue to the ſoule bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of many.</note> be imployed to the ſeruice and immediate ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of almightie God. But I hope theſe ſpeaches ſhall not neede, and that the example of Nehemiah that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and zealous Prince, will bee followed in this caſe, he hauing the feare of God before his eies, being twelue yeares gouernour ouer the people that returned from Babell:<note place="margin">Nehe. 5.10.14.</note> when his labour was to builde the wall of Ieruſalem, and to ſet vppe the puritie of religion: that hee might giue good example to the Princes and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and that the people might no way bee ouer char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that ſo the buſineſſe of the Lord might go cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and proſperouſlie forward, as it did indeede. Hee not onely tooke nothing to him, which was due vnto him, as hee was chiefe Gouernour, but alſo ſpent of that which he had of his ovvne, for the common charges of the wall, and fedde many at his table, lent his money to the poore, redeemed them that vvere captiue, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſeruaunts to doe the like in their place, and that all of them came to helpe forvvard the vvorke. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Iehoaſh King of Iuda, is very memorable for this purpoſe,<note place="margin">2. Kings 12.</note> when the prieſts had neglected the repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the decaied places of the Temple (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Kings commandement) till the three &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth yeare of his raigne. The charge and money for that buſineſſe vvas committed to others, who vvere ſo farre from gaining by it, that they ſhewed ſuch faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe in doing of it, that it was not thought needfull that they ſhould giue any accounts of their dooing. If euer it pleaſe GOD to giue reformation amongeſt vs, I pray God that this mercy in framing of the heartes of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:728:51"/>al ſortes and degrees, after the good of theſe examples, may bee alſo a bleſſing vpon vs, as I hope that through his tender compaſſion and bounty it will.</p>
            <p>Now as great a matter ſtandeth in the ſecond point, how this ſhalbe ordered: one ſaith that it would be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good, that it ſhould be all, and all the other church li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings likewiſe taken out of the miniſters hands, and that they ſhould haue their ſeuerall penſions or ſtipends of a reaſonable ſort,<note place="margin">To put al the miniſters to their penſions were not good.</note> for this ſaith he, would be eaſieſt and quieteſt, ſo that they ſhould be troubled with nothing, but to follow their bookes, and looke to their charge: if it might be ſo indeed, as theſe words do roundly beare vs in hand in very good ſhew, it were the beſt, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie miniſter would be glad of the quieteſt way, and moſt benefit to the church. Another peraduenture is of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers mind, &amp; thinketh it very inconuenient, eſpecially at this time, when there is a ſettled prouiſion for moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that by ſuch a meanes, as is no great trouble to the miniſter, that wil not wilfully be a loyterer. It is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to keepe a good way which we haue, then to follow a new, and change for the worſe: and truly this latter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth moſt with pollicy for the ſtate, and with benefite for the church: for the ſtate, it is found a point of tryed policy to alter as few things as may be, (eſpecially when they are good and well) wherein the people haue had a long cuſtome or intereſt, for this is a way vnto murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, diſcontentment, ſtirs and ſedition, and the people will quickly ſuſpect, that for the priuate gaine of ſome fewe, ſuch thinges are inuented, when they ſee plainly that it is very well already. I doubt it will bee found a hard meaſure to ſome, an vnluckie peece of worke to begin, heauy in the carriage, and a day of blacknes vnto poſteritie. Secondly, there muſt bee offices erected and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:728:51"/>augmented, and a great many men muſt haue leaſes or ſome other authoritie and office to gather the fruits: and what will come of this (which requireth many deuices) a man cannot tell at the firſt fight, neither ſhall he ſee all the miſchiefs till it be practiſed: but this muſt needs fall out, that many men for gathering the fruites, for recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and paying againe, muſt haue a fleece, and ſo the church ſhalbe ſhortned &amp; ſhorne of her right, by a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les occupation: when the people ſhal pay peraduenture well the more, for he that hireth muſt liue by it: againe, when the right &amp; property is out of the churches hold: it may offer occaſion in time, that it ſhall bee taken away altogeather, and then there will be iniury to the church and oppreſſion of the people.</p>
            <p>But the other is euery way better: Firſt, it is eaſier to be done when there remaineth no more but the due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations of the liuinges,<note place="margin">The ready way to prouide for miniſters.</note> and to redeeme the impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations, and to augment the ſmaller liuings: it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ſuſpicion, for we ſee the practiſe, we know it to be good, and neede not feare any ill to come of it: and it is more iuſt, for then the whole liuing goeth that waye it ſhould, and the people wil the better away with it, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, becauſe they ſee it is beſtowed according to their mind, &amp; partly, becauſe they are likely to be better vſed and the miniſter for his part ſhall be better able to keepe hoſpitality, &amp; to feed the pore by the vſe of ſuch things as ariſe by that meanes, and that which is no ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, hee may let out part or all, as hee ſhall find moſt for his eaſe, and beſt for his profite, and if there doe any benefit ariſe, this openeth the doore to him, wheras the other way penneth him in to one certaine place, bee it good or be it bad: and it may be, that his neighbours of good will for his eaſe, will gather his fruits for him, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:728:52"/>he ſhal ſaue al, that by the other way ſhould be loſt, both to him and the people: Briefly, the more one looketh in the compariſon of theſe two wais, the more he ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that the order nowe eſtabliſhed, is the beſt: if the impropriations were redeemed, and the ſmall liuinges increaſed. Now for the furthering of this good worke, there are two things to be added, which will helpe this matter very well:<note place="margin">Vniting of ſmal liuings one help to the miniſtery</note> Firſt, the vniting of diuers little pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes in one, a thing of common practiſe, out of which commeth this commodity, the liuing is increaſed: and by the number of the people, there are the more wiſe men to bee choſen for Eccleſiaſticall officers: and the church ſhal be the more cumly, and as eaſily taught in a maner.<note place="margin">Benefices with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cure may be ſome helpe, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler liuinges.</note> The next is, there are certaine thinges ſcattered heere and there without cure, theſe may bee ioyned to helpe the ſmaller liuings.</p>
            <p>Then as touching the impropriations: in ſome there is great eaſe,<note place="margin">Reſigning and redeeming of Impropriations by Bb. &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall liuings wil be a good meanes to main taine a learned miniſtery.</note> &amp; in ſome there is no great hardnes. Thoſe which be in L. Bb. hands, and pertaining to theſe great churches, may eaſily be redeemed, if they be ſent from whence they came: there need be no charge: and I dout not, but the third part will bee thus redeemed: but if there bee any in the Queenes poſſeſſion, or of any tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall man, or in Colledges, the landes and houſes and other temporalities of the L.Bb. and other great Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches may be imployed to redeeme them: If the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and account of theſe things, bee committed to wiſe and godly men, inhabiting in euery ſhire,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 18.4.</note> vvhere ſuch liuings &amp; churches are (as Ioſhua appointed 3. of euery tribe to walke through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land to deſcribe it) it wil eaſily be found out, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuing of the miniſtery will be brought to a good and cumly meaſure: and that euery Church would haue at the leaſt two hundreth markes
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:728:52"/>yearly for the Paſtour and teacher, and ſome aboue two hundred pound,<note place="margin">Tith wood me dowe, &amp;c. might helpe in ſome places.</note> which might alſo bee holpen in ſome places by tithe wood and medowe, and a greater ſiſe of paſture, where ſuch things are either not paied, or not according to the value of the tenths by much.</p>
            <p>But here groweth a queſtion:<note place="margin">The overplus of Bb. and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral liuinges may pay firſt fruites, tenthes, ſubſidies &amp;c.</note> What if the L.Bb. and the Cathedrall churches come to more then will ſerue for the redeeming of the impropriations, or leſſe: If more, (as I am verely perſwaded it will) it may ſerue to recompence the wonted firſt fruites and tenthes, which were from theſe ſeas and churches, it may ſerue to erect in all ſhires, a Lecture of al ſciences, that ſuch as cannot put their ſonnes to Cambridge and Oxford, may haue them in the free Schooles, and after by thoſe Lectures brought through all arts: which would greatly increaſe learned and wiſe men in this land, and make a floriſhing time.</p>
            <p>But if it ſhould fall ſhort of our reckoning,<note place="margin">If Bb. and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall liuings be too little: a general beneuo lence will make it vp.</note> there is yet an eaſie helpe, that is, a free beneuolence, and as it were an offring of all ſortes of people, yong and old through this land: this way hath the church of God beene verie much holpen and aduanced, and who is it that will not be willing to further ſuch a worthy, honorable and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worke. In the time of Moſes,<note place="margin">Exod. 36.5.6.</note> when hee built the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, &amp; made the altars &amp; prieſts garments,<note place="margin">Our for fathers liberal in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge to the Church.</note> things of a wonderfull great charge, for gold, ſiluer, ſilke, preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, incenſe and all coſtly thinges: The people came ſo willingly, and offered ſo plentifully, that there was to much, ſo that Moſes proclaimed that they ſhuld offer no more.<note place="margin">2. Chron. 31.4.</note> And when Hezekiah commaunded to bring a part to the prieſts and leuites, to incourage them in the lawe, they brought in ſuch abundance, that they did eat and were filled, and yet there remained plentie
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:728:53"/>in heapes that they had made. And in Dauids time for the building of the Temple,<note place="margin">1. Chron. 29.6.</note> the Princes of the families, and the Princes of the tribes of Iſraell, and the captains of thouſandes, and of hundrethes, with the rulers of the kings worke, offered willingly, and gaue for the houſe of God, fiue thouſand talents of golde, and 10000. pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; 10000. talents of ſiluer, 18000. talents of braſſe, 100000. talents of Iron, and they with whom precious ſtones were found, gaue them to the treaſure: and the people reioyced when they offered willingly, for they offered willingly vnto the Lord, with a perfect hart, and Dauid the king alſo reioyced with great ioy. And there is no reaſon to feare the contrary in our time, of which it is written: the people ſhall offer willingly in the time of the aſſembly.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 110.3.</note> I doubt not therefore of Gods mercie and bleſſing, if wee were as forward to go about ſuch a matter, with ſinglenes of heart, and ſimplicity of Godly wiſedome, and would follow after it with earneſtnes of zeale, and painfulnes of knowledge, forgetting our own eaſe, pleaſure, wealth and will, to preferre the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, the benefite of our ſoules, the glory of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, vnto the praiſe of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and this would bee the glory of our land. For thus ſpeaketh God vnto his owne people, whom he honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with his word. Bring ye all the tithes into the ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.10.</note> that there may be meat in my houſe, and prooue me nowe herewith, if I will not open the windowes of heauen vnto you, ſaith the Lord of hoaſtes, if I will not open the windows of heauen vnto you, and power you out a bleſſing without meaſure, &amp; I will rebuke the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer for your ſakes: and he ſhall not deſtroy the fruit of your ground, neither ſhall your vine be barren in the field, ſaith the Lord of hoaſts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:728:53"/>
If I ſhould ſtay here, I might be accuſed either of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice or cruelty, of vniuſtice, bicaus I haue but ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken of her Majeſties due, in the firſt fruits, tenths, and ſubſidie of the Cleargy (as they call it) and of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations neuer a word. The firſt of theſe is the greateſt doubt: for if the common wealth ſtand in need (as it is likely in this troubleſome time) then there is good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that al men help without any priuiledge, in aſmuch as euery one hath part of the benefit &amp; comfort, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, I am perſwaded that the royall and chriſtian heart of her Majeſty, would as willingly part from it, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially the firſt fruits and tenths, knowing howe they came in, as euer Dauid did,<note place="margin">1. Chron. 29.3.4.</note> who conſidering that it was the houſe of God and not man, and becauſe hee had a delight in the houſe of his God, beſides the great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration which he made, of gold, braſſe, yron, ſiluer, &amp; pretious ſtones of diuers ſorts for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſanctuary, he gaue of his own, three thouſand talents of gold of Ophir, &amp; ſeuen thouſand talents of fined ſiluer.</p>
            <p>Firſt it may bee ſeene,<note place="margin">Howe firſt fruites, tenthes &amp; ſubſidies of Bb. &amp; Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral churches may be payde notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they be ſolde to redeme impropriations</note> whether the ouerplus of the lands, after the impropriations bee redeemed, there be not ſufficient to repay the valu of ſo much, as the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of thoſe firſt fruits tenths and ſubſidies of L.Bb. and Cathedrall churches do amount, which if it do (as I verely thinke it will, and ſpare if thinges bee handled wiſely &amp; with a perfect heart) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there need no further dealing for recompence:<note place="margin">1. by the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus.</note> &amp; al other churches may be as in times paſt: but if not,<note place="margin">2. by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</note> then the foreſaid beneuolence may ſtop the gap for the redeeming of the foreſaid im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations, that the landes may remaine to this vſe of buying out of the ſaid firſt fruits, which wold be a great eaſe to the church, and the burden would not be great, at once to giue, euery man a little of his ſuperfluity, to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:728:54"/>haue a continuall benefit for euer: Beſides that, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie would be better able, and willing at all times, if need be, to giue a beneuolence, to further all neceſſarie purpoſes to the eaſe of the common welth, as a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of this kindnes.</p>
            <p>Beſides this if need be,<note place="margin">3. By the ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which are increaſed.</note> thoſe liuings that be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the reſtored impropriations, or otherwiſe: may be ſet vp to hier and greater firſt fruits, tenths and ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: and where three or fower, leſſe or more bee made one, they may followe the rate of ſo many, ſo that there need bee no diminiſhing of the treaſure of the land by this alteration, except it pleaſe her highnes, of her graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bounty, vppon the triall of gods rare bleſſinges to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes her and her people, to mittigate ſome part, as a drink offering of a ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice vnto almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God: knowing that he can a thouſand maner of wais ſend it in againe by other means, with great intereſt and increaſe, as it is written.<note place="margin">Prou. 11.25.</note> The liberall perſon ſhall haue plenty, &amp; he that watereth ſhall alſo haue raine. He that ſoweth ſparingly,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.6.8.</note> ſhall reape ſparingly, and he that ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth liberally ſhal reape alſo liberally, and God is able to make all graces abound towards you, that ye alwais ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all ſufficiency in all thinges, may abound in euerie good worke.<note place="margin">Prou. 10.22.</note> The bleſſing of the Lorde, it maketh rich, and he doth ad no ſorrows with it.<note place="margin">Deut. 28.1.3.5.6.7.12.</note> Againe, if thou ſhalt diligently obey the voyce of the Lord thy God, bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the city, and in the field, in thy basket, and in thy dough, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou commeſt in, &amp; when thou goeſt out, the Lorde ſhall cauſe thine enemies that riſe againſt thee, to fall before thy face, they ſhall come out againſt thee one way, and flie before thee ſeuen waies, and the Lorde ſhall bring vpon thee his good treaſure, euen the heauen to giue rain to thy land in due ſeaſon,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:728:54"/>and to bleſſe all the worke of thy hands, and thou ſhalt lend vnto many nations, and ſhalt not borrow thy ſelf.</p>
            <p>As touching Preſentations, it would be a very good and commendable thing,<note place="margin">Of preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> if they were contained in the free gift of Prince and people, to bee reſigned to euerie church, which by the laws of Diſcipline, ought to haue their free choice of their miniſters. It will be no loſſe to the patrons, except a man wil ſtand vpon a dignity. For euery man holdeth it Symony, for patrons to take anie rewards or gaine, and men are ſworne againſt it. But if it ſhal not be thought good ſo to do, the order that now is of preſenting of able and ſufficient Clearkes may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, ſo there be ſufficient caution that the Cannon of Chriſt be not broken, the order of his Diſcipline viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor the church wherto he ſhalbe preſented robbed of their right in election. Yet in all theſe things I prefer not mine owne iudgement or wiſedome,<note place="margin">An humble caution of the Author.</note> neither doe I ſet it down as the iudgement of al or many of them that ſeeke the reformation: but as I haue often ſayd, I ſubmit this my priuate motion, to your honorable wiſedomes, and to all godly learned men, that if a better and eaſier way may be found, this may bee reiected, onely I craue that the thinges and my reaſons, firſt and laſt, may bee rightly waighed, and that if a better cannot bee found, this may be wiſely conſidered and not neglected.</p>
            <p>Now in the ſecond place it were cruelty (ſaith ſom) to put down theſe ſpirituall lords, and great men of the church, and to turne them into ſmall liuings, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to turne out the vnfitte men: it were pittie to ſee them, their wiues and their children to be put to miſery and begging. If a man ſhould make compariſon with their doinges, what pitty eought there to bee ſhewed vpon them, which iuſtly for breaking Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:728:55"/>are turned out, when there is no pitty ſhewed to ſuch as ſtande to Gods trueth,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.6.7.12.13.</note> and breake onely the traditions of men:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.16.</note> To the one, the ſcripture pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth woe, and therefore why ſhould they be pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?<note place="margin">Mat. 15.9.</note> to the other, the ſcripture ioyneth in league as it were, pronouncing vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mercy, &amp; ſaith with them againſt the other. In vaine doe you worſhip God, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching for doctrine the traditions of men, why ſhould not they be pittied?</p>
            <p>As touching the L.Bb. and great clergy men, which haue ſoe laden themſelues with thicke claye, that they haue much adoe to get vp in the pulpit of God:<note place="margin">Haback. 2.6.</note> doe they not know that it is their duty, that they may pleaſe him who hath choſen them to bee his ſouldiars, not to intangle themſelues with the affairs of this life,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.4.</note> and that they ought for the peace and wealth of the church, to followe the example of their Lord and Maiſter Chriſt Ieſus and to haue his minde in them, who being God, made him ſelfe of no reputation and tooke vppon him the forme of a ſeruant,<note place="margin">Philip. 2.5.</note> and was made like vnto men, and was found in ſhape as a man, and humbled himſelfe &amp; became obedient vnto death, euen the death of the croſſe,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.9.</note> &amp; he being rich became poore that wee through his pouerty might be made riche: then is it a ſmal mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them to leaue their thouſands,<note place="margin">The Bb. &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral prelats, if they be fit, may be applied to ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer churches of good liuing.</note> and bee content with their hundrethes: and ſurely I hope ſo of the men that they wil: for God forbid that they ſhoulde be of that curſed crue of vnbeleeuers: who they knowe loue the praiſe of men more then of God: &amp; ſeeking honour one of an other,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.44.</note> ſeeke not the honour that commeth of God alone: or of thoſe vnfaithful ſtewardes, which ſeck their owne,<note place="margin">Philip. 2.21. cap. 3.19.20.</note> and not that which is Chriſt Ieſus, or of thoſe damnable bellye gods: whoſe glory is to their
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:728:55"/>ſhame, and mind earthly things, when all the true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters haue their conuerſation in heauen.</p>
            <p>As for the other, which by no meanes can be fitted to bee workemen, and to labour in Gods building and husbandry: although they are worthie of nothing for their preſumption and raſh entring where they ſhould not,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.13.</note> but as vnſauery ſalt to be caſt forth and trode vnder foot of men, eſpecially ſuch vnthrifts, as beeing broken from liuing by their trades, or are thruſt out of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely occupation of a ſeruiture, do chooſe as their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and for an eaſie life to be in the miniſtery:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.10.</note> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Church is to correct her children to edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and not deſtruction: and the lawe of charity wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth to do good vnto al men, yea vnto them that haue done vs euill,<note place="margin">Vnable mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed may haue ſome ſtocke: or a ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pende for their life time.</note> and it may pleaſe God by this meanes to giue them repentaunce, it may bee a verie good thing, that theſe haue a ſtipend for their life time, or ſom ſtock to helpe them that are not able to get their liuing other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by their trades: and eſpecially ſuch as beeing verie honeſt men at the beginning of her Maieſties raigne, were drawen in of ſimplicity, not knowing the great burden of the calling: onely heerein they haue greatlie offended, that through idlenes they haue not, in al this time, attained to any knowledge fit for that calling, and they haue bene diuers waies admoniſhed, yet ſome may be one degree more charitably thoght of, becauſe they haue ſo ſmall liuing, that they are driuen to labour and care, to make it holde out, beeing burdened with verie many and too heauy paiments.</p>
            <p>And in this point, the honorable and noble care of King Henry the eight, hath purchaſed his due praiſe in giuing ſtipendes or penſions, for the life time of them that were turned out of the Abbies and Monaſteries
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:728:56"/>which were no more worthy to bee ſuffered in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, then theſe L.Bb. and vnpreching prelacie: &amp; it wil be found a better thing &amp; eſier for the church, a little while to beare the burden of theſe mens penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or ſtockes, then to ſuffer the Church to be damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by them for euer: for wee ſee that it is a broode of ſuch a nature that will hardly be weeded out, except this good way of turning them out togither be taken in hand: and while men will looke to doe it by little and little, a time wilfal out, that they wil wax too ſtrong: &amp; oppreſſe the good miniſters as the Cananites did Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el vnder Iabin twenty yeeres.<note place="margin">Iudg. 4.1.2.</note> Delay is dangerous, and curſed is hee that doth the worke of the Lord looſely or negligently.</p>
            <p>But what ſhould I run through euery thing: I knowe your honorable wiſedomes can doe a great deal more ſufficiently in the conſideration, ſearching, &amp; applying, of euery thing to his proper place, that God hath raiſed vp at your hands, very notable men which are endued with giftes:<note place="margin">Exod. 35.30.34.</note> which like vnto Bezaleel and Aholiab are filled with an excellent ſpirit of wiſedome and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and knowledg in al the worke of God, and to teach other likewiſe. Therefore as this is euery way the fitteſt time for ſuch a holy and honorable purpoſe, ſo I thought I was in conſcience to make known, that which hath diuerſly and many times bene aduiſed of in my minde, as it were by an humble motion to bring to your remembraunce, that which I hope you cannot be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of: and in ſome ſorte to enter you in that, which I truſt you are willing and forward vnto, and to drawe that out with a coal, as it were rudly, which you by good aduiſe and mature judgment, may bring forth &amp; make perfect with great profit, beuty and glory. And I referre
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:728:56"/>al that I haue done, vnto your honorable wiſe and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſure, that if I haue ſwarued any thing from the word of God, or good reaſon agreing to the ſame, it might be reiected, proteſting that I meddle not with any mans perſon, but with the cauſe, and vnderſtand &amp; meane when I reprehende ſome mens doinges in the naming of the perſons, onely by the title of their place, the thing which is the ground and occaſion of ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: which being taken away, I ſuppoſe the euil of ſuch perſons wilbe purged. And thus in all humbleneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring your Honours, and all wiſe menne, to conſider in the feare of God of euery thing, without prejudice to the truth, or affection to men or times: from my very ſoule I commend you to the tuition and gouerment of almighty God, and whome from the bottome of my heart, in feare and trembling, I doe pray and beſeech, to powre downe the ritches of his graces vppon vs all, in al wiſedome and ſpiritual vnderſtanding, that wee may walke worthy of the Lord, and pleaſe him in all things, and namely vpon his Annointed and gratious handmayde, Elizabeth our deare Soueraigne Lady &amp; Queene, to bleſſe her with longe dayes, and good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, with daylie increaſe of honour before God &amp; men, and joy of heart in the holy Ghoſt: and that we al which are vnder her, may worſhip our true and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, according to his worde: in truth, ſincerity and vprightnes, and liue in al faithful duty to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and godly loue one with another, being bleſſed with peace wealth and godlines, from generation to generation, through Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour, to whome with the Father and the holy ſpirit, one God, be al honour &amp; glory for euer AMEN.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:728:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:728:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
